<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Manish Barnwal</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://manishbarnwal.github.io/</id><updated>2017-01-27T08:00:00-02:00</updated><entry><title>Visualization aka EDA is way too under-rated</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2017/01/27/visualization_is_under-rated/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-01-27T08:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2017-01-27:blog/2017/01/27/visualization_is_under-rated/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Visualization is one of the most important pillars of data science. Every one wants to learn Machine learning but if you explain them the little tasks that involve the overall workflow of the process, it turns them off. Everyone just wants to do the cool stuff. They want to build models and be done with it. And I was one of them. I understand that feeling when you get the data and without much understanding of the features in the dataset, we just want to throw in the data to a model and hope that something good comes out.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I have participated in many hacks relating to ML and I used to just hope the trained model would do the task. Sadly, this thought always betrayed me. Even ensemble of various models may not work. Sometimes there are patterns in data which one gets to know only when one does EDA, when one plots a few graphs. One tries to understand the relationship of one feature with the other or do univariate analysis of the columns. An ML model is not always sufficient to understand the patterns in data.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
After a point, the learning of a model becomes saturated. It can only perform to a certain point. If there is a pattern that you have identified, it would definitely help the model to better train on it.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I have learnt this hard way - You can't ignore EDA, visualization if you want to come in the top 1% of the leaderboard. Anyone and everyone can run a random forest model. Tuning the parameters is a little tedious but that too can be done with little practice. But finding the hidden patterns in the dataset, finding the relationship, understanding the little nuances in the data is an art. It's a skill. It takes practice. A lot of practice.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I have always wondered, how does the winners go about finding those patterns. Isn't there a course that could teach me these hacks to find the unseen patterns. Unfortunately, there are courses that teaches EDA, they teach you how to use ggplot2. But the thing I am talking about takes altogether a different mindset. One needs to be patient with this chunk of work. There are no defined paths to it. You just keep doing the EDA, observe the patterns, try to create new features based on this and once you have done this a hundred times, then you realize you finally understand this thing.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;So how do you master the art of EDA?&lt;/strong&gt;
The short answer is practice. But then how do you practice EDA? You take shorter assignments, try to write the code snippet of common plots like histogram, scatterplot, bar-plot. And when you plot these graphs, I would strongly recommend to use &lt;em&gt;ggplot2&lt;/em&gt; if you are using R. In one of the talks, Hadley Wickham has strongly asserted that one should start learning visualization using &lt;em&gt;ggplot2&lt;/em&gt;. The syntax is very intuitive and makes plots interesting and beautiful. And when a person like Hadley advises a thing, you just follow it.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I have learnt more about R by looking at other people's codes. Look at the Kernels shared on &lt;a href="www.Kaggle.com"&gt;Kaggle&lt;/a&gt; by the top performers of Kaggle. The kind of analysis they do is just mind-blowing. And the best part is they share the code for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I would just share the code snippets for the most common visualization tasks. Below are some of the most common plots to know about your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Barplot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt; ggplot(data = mpg) +
  geom_bar(mapping = aes(x = as.factor(class))) +
  ggtitle(label = 'Plot of class of vehicle') +
  xlab('Class of vehicle') + ylab('Count')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Scatterplot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scatterplot is useful for displaying the relationship between two continuous variables, although it can also be used with one continuous and one categorical variable, or two categorical variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt; ggplot(data = mpg) +
  geom_point(mapping = aes(x = displ, y = hwy)) +
  ggtitle(label = 'Plot of engine size v/s mileage') +
  xlab('Engine size (litres)') + ylab('Highway mileage')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Linechart plot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt; ggplot(data = mpg) +
  geom_line(mapping = aes(x = displ, y = hwy)) +
  ggtitle(label = 'Plot of engine size v/s mileage') +
  xlab('Engine size (litres)') + ylab('Highway mileage')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will add a tutorial on visualization in R using &lt;strong&gt;ggplot2&lt;/strong&gt; soon. Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="ML"></category><category term="data science"></category></entry><entry><title>The filmy Secret Santa</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/12/22/filmy_secret_santa/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-12-22T07:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-12-22:blog/2016/12/22/filmy_secret_santa/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever heard of secret Santa game? If not, you may not appreciate this article. Wait till you join the corporate world. But if you have, secret Santa may ring some bell.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Dialogues define our cinema. Ever imagined this twist. What if the Secret Santa gets introduced to Bollywood? Presenting, &lt;em&gt;Secret Santa meets Bollywood!&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="bade_bade" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/bade_bade.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bade bade companies me aise chhote chhote tasks milte rehte hai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="thappad" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/thappad.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gift se dar nahi lagta saheb, task se lagta hai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="rahul_naam" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/rahul_naam.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secret Santa, naam toh suna hi hoga&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="sahensha" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/sahensha.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rishte me toh hum tumhare Secret Santa lagte hai, naam hum hints ke through bataenge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="lion" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/lion.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saara office mujhe Secret Santa ke naam se jaanta hai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="tareekh" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/tareekh.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tasks pe tasks, tasks pe tasks, tasks pe tasks milti rahi hai magar hints na mila. Mile toh bas tasks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="feke_paise" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/feke_paise.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Main aaj bhi feke hue hints nahi uthata&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="picture_abhi" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/picture_abhi.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tasks abhi baaki hai mere dost&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="babu_moshai" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/babu_moshai.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Babu moshai, hints interesting hone chahiye lambe nahi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="batman" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/batman.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;It's not the gift that matters...but the task given by your Secret Santa that defines you&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img alt="winter" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/winter.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secret Santa is coming&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
That is all for now, folks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is your favorite Bollywood dialogue in this list? Drop down your Secret Santa dialogues in comments.   &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Christmas"></category><category term="office"></category></entry><entry><title>Fix you | Ghar aa jaao</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/11/24/ghar_aa_jaao/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-11-24T07:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-11-24:blog/2016/11/24/ghar_aa_jaao/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month on a mundane weekend, I was practicing this song - Fix you by Coldplay when my friend, Dipu came to the room. He stood there for some time to understand what I was trying to play. I am not that pro on guitar yet. Chances are you may want to throw me and my guitar out of your sight.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
After some trouble, Dipu finally guessed the song and randomly uttered some lines in Hindi along the tune of the original song. And when he was bored, he left the room. I continued my attempt to make the song perfect on the guitar. It was then when I thought what if I write the complete song in Hindi along the tune of the original.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Without much thought, I picked up my notebook and started scribbling few lines. Later, Dipu also joined me in this attempt and below is the final song that we came up with.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Verse 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab har koshish pe ho jaati hai haar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab milta nahi jo ho tera pyaar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab saath nahin ho mera wo yaar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Akela hoon main...&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Verse 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab lagta hai sab gaya hai bikhar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab lagta hai suna, bin tere sheher&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab aati nahi ho tum nazar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sab kuch hai soo... oo... na&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghar aa jaao tum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sath seh lenge hum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kal fir aayega&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Verse 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sadkon pe hoon, ab main khada&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aakhon me hain, bas chehra tera&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur hoton pe hai, bas vaada tera&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tujh sang hamesha...aaa&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghar aa jaao tum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sath seh lenge hum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kal fir aayega&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bridge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aasoon bahein, tere chehre pe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur main kuch na kar paaya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aasoon bahein, tere chehre pe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur main...&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aasoo bahein tere chehre pe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur main bebas hoon yahan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aasoo bahein tere chehre pe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur main...&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghar aa jaao tum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sath seh lenge hum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kal fir aayega&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghar aa jaao tum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sath seh lenge hum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kal fir aayega&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The practice is on. Hopefully, we will have the song recorded and if it's worth listening to, I will upload it on my &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCbZuY83yIUrbm0dZYP9eFHw/videos?view=0&amp;amp;sort=dd&amp;amp;shelf_id=0"&gt;Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Coldplay"></category></entry><entry><title>Random Forest explained intuitively</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/10/18/random_forest_explained_intuitively/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-10-18T08:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-10-18:blog/2016/10/18/random_forest_explained_intuitively/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Random Forests algorithm has always fascinated me. I like how this algorithm can be easily explained to anyone without much hassle. One quick example, I use very frequently to explain the working of random forests is the way a company has multiple rounds of interview to hire a candidate. Let me elaborate.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Say, you appeared for the position of Statistical analyst at WalmartLabs. Now like most of the companies, you don't just have one round of interview. You have multiple rounds of interviews. Each of these interviews is chaired by independent panels. Each panel assess the candidate separately and independently. Generally, even the questions asked in these interviews differ from each other. Randomness is important here.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
If you have heard about decision tree, then you are not very far from understanding what random forests are. Random forests is a forest of many decision trees. So you now understand why is it called forest.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why is it called random then?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say our dataset has 1,000 rows and 30 columns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two levels of randomness in this algorithm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At row level&lt;/strong&gt;: Each of these decision trees gets a random sample of the training data (say 10%) i.e. each of these trees will be trained independently on 100 randomly chosen rows out of 1,000 rows of data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At column level&lt;/strong&gt;: The second level of randomness is introduced at the column level. Not all the columns are passed into training each of the decision trees. Say we want only 10% of columns to be sent to each tree. This means a randomly selected 3 column will be sent to each tree. So for first decision tree, may be column C1, C2 and C4 were chosen. The next DT will have C4, C5, C10 as chosen columns and so on.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Let me draw an analogy now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us now understand how interview selection process resembles a random forest algorithm. Each panel in the interview process is actually a decision tree. Each panel gives a result whether the candidate is a pass or fail and then a majority of these results is declared as final. Say there were 5 panels, 3 said yes and 2 said no. The final verdict will be yes.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Something similar happens in random forest as well. The results from each of the tree is taken and final result is declared accordingly. Voting and averaging is used to predict in case of classification and regression respectively.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
With the advent of huge computational power at our disposal, we hardly think for even a second before we apply random forests. And very conveniently our predictions are made. Let us try to understand other aspects of this algorithm.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;When is a random forest a poor choice relative to other algorithms?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Random forests doesn't train well on smaller datasets&lt;/strong&gt; as it fails to pick on the pattern. To simplify, say we know that 1 pen costs INR 1, 2 pens cost INR 2, 3 pens cost INR 6. In this case linear regression will easily estimate the cost of 4 pens but random forests will fail to come up with a good estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is a problem of interpretability with random forest.&lt;/strong&gt; You can't see or understand the relationship between the response and the dependent variables. Understand that RF is a predictive tool and not a descriptive tool. You get variable importance but this may not suffice in many analysis of interests where the objective might be to see the relationship between response and the independent features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;time taken to train random forests&lt;/strong&gt; may sometimes be too huge as you train multiple decision trees. Also, in case of categorical variable, the time complexity increases exponentially. For a categorical column with n levels, RF tries split at 2^n -1 points to find the maximal splitting point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of regression problem, &lt;strong&gt;the range of values response variable can take&lt;/strong&gt; is determine by the values already available in the training dataset. Unlike linear regression, RF can't take on value outside the training data.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are the advantages of using random forest?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we are using multiple decision trees, &lt;strong&gt;the bias remains same as that of a single decision tree&lt;/strong&gt;. However, the variance decreases and thus we decrease the chances of overfitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When all you care about is the predictions and &lt;strong&gt;want a quick and dirty way-out&lt;/strong&gt;, random forest comes to the rescue.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I will add in the R code snippets as well to get an idea of how this is executed soon.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts on the topic in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="random forest"></category><category term="ml"></category><category term="data-science"></category></entry><entry><title>Improve runtime of Random Forest in R</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/10/13/improve_runtime_random_forest_r/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-10-13T10:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-10-13:blog/2016/10/13/improve_runtime_random_forest_r/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are two ways one can write the code to train a random forest model in R.
Both the ways are listed below.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
A normal and frequent way of writing the command to train the random forest model is something like this.
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;rfModel &amp;lt;- randomForest(Survived~. , data = trainSample[, -c(6, 8, 9)])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice the &lt;strong&gt;~&lt;/strong&gt; sign. We call this the formula way of writing.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Another way of writing the command to train the random forest model is shown below.
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;rfModel &amp;lt;- randomForest(y=trainSample$Survived, x= trainSample[, -c(6, 8, 9)], data = trainSample)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we explicitly mention the y-variable and the x variables.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Recently, I was working on a huge dataset where the task was to predict a variable based on some 12 independent variables. The dataset had close to 1.3 million rows. I tried train the model using the first method i.e the formula way. Sadly, I had to kill the task as it was taking a lot of time.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It was then, I got to know that if you train the model using the second format command, the code runs relatively faster. When investigated further, I got to know that the reason for the difference in time is that the code for random forest is written in C and when one writes in the &lt;em&gt;formula format&lt;/em&gt;, the x and y variables are explicitly converted into proper format and this is what takes time. &lt;a href="http://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/116952/improving-randomforest-running-time"&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Even the help page of randomForest in R says the same thing.
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;?randomForest
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For large data sets, especially those with large number of variables, calling randomForest via the formula interface is not advised: There may be too much overhead in handling the formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Look just before the 'Authors' section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time difference is not significant for smaller datasets. However, for larger datasets I would suggest using the second format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the time difference, I have taken a dataset having 2,23,874 rows and 6 columns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;system.time( rfModel1 &lt;- randomForest(DepDelay~. , data = subset(df, select = c(1,2,3,4,5, 13))) )
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;user  system elapsed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;94.582  11.356 &lt;strong&gt;109.311&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;system.time( rfModel2 &lt;-randomForest(y=df$DepDelay, x=df[,c(1,2,3,4,5)], data=subset(df, select = c(1,2,3,4,5, 13))) )
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;user  system elapsed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;93.499  10.248 &lt;strong&gt;106.205&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shows a time difference of 3 seconds. Note that all of these columns were numeric and if one takes categorical columns as well, the time difference would be more.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Also, this dataset is not huge. One would appreciate this more on larger datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts on the topic in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="learnings"></category><category term="thoughts"></category></entry><entry><title>How to install a package of a particular version in R</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/10/05/install_a_package_particular_version_in_R/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-10-05T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-10-05:blog/2016/10/05/install_a_package_particular_version_in_R/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently tried installing &lt;em&gt;caret&lt;/em&gt; package in R using
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;install.packages('caret', dependencies=T)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally this installation of package works and I continue to work with the functions associated with the package.
When I tried including the package using
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;library(caret)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got the following error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;Error in loadNamespace(j &lt;- i[[1L]], c(lib.loc, .libPaths()), versionCheck = vI[[j]]) :there is no package called 'pbkrtest'
In addition: Warning message:package 'caret' was built under R version 3.2.5
Error: package or namespace load failed for 'caret'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R was not able to install this dependency package- &lt;em&gt;pbkrtest&lt;/em&gt;. So I tried installing it separately, again using
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;install.package('pbkrtest', dependencies=T)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This too didn't work. And the error again this time was
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;Error in loadNamespace(j &amp;lt;- i[[1L]], c(lib.loc, .libPaths()), versionCheck = vI[[j]]) : there is no package called ‘pbkrtest’ In addition: Warning message: package ‘pbkrtest’ was built under R version 3.2.3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this particular package is not available for the R version that I am using.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What is the way out?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We install an older version of this package.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do you install an older version of some package in R?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will go ahead with package-&lt;em&gt;pbkrtest&lt;/em&gt; to illustrate the steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open this &lt;a href="https://cran.r-project.org/src/contrib/Archive/pbkrtest"&gt;url&lt;/a&gt;. You will see various versions of the package listed there. Choose the version you want to install. Let's say I want to install the &lt;em&gt;pbkrtest_0.4-5.tar.gz&lt;/em&gt; version.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now create a variable &lt;em&gt;packageUrl&lt;/em&gt; which contains all this information and assign it the url of the page.
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;packageUrl&amp;lt;- "https://cran.r-project.org/src/contrib/Archive/pbkrtest/pbkrtest_0.4-5.tar.gz"
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You then install this version of the package using
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;install.packages(packageUrl, repos=NULL, type='source')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we are done!
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now if you have some other package to install, just replace the last word &lt;em&gt;pbkrtest&lt;/em&gt; with the package name you want to install and you will be able to see all the older versions of that package. For &lt;em&gt;Rcpp&lt;/em&gt; the link would be &lt;a href="https://cran.r-project.org/src/contrib/Archive/Rcpp"&gt;url&lt;/a&gt;. Choose the version you want to install and follow the steps stated above.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts on the topic in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manish&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="R"></category></entry><entry><title>Don’t introduce that bias in your child</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/10/02/bias_in_child/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-10-02T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-10-02:blog/2016/10/02/bias_in_child/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A thought crossed my mind yesterday and just when it was about to get lost in the cloud of many thoughts that scatters in mind…I caught hold of it. I felt I had gathered the maximum out of this thought but I wanted to write about it so that the mind has to think more on it and may be, just may be, I will be able to know more.
Here’s the thought.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every child learns something or the other from every human it spends time with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This statement sounds more promising when we think about it in this context. We tend to become more like our parents because we spend maximum time with them. Our characters and behaviors are imitated from theirs.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
How does it happen that a &lt;em&gt;baniya&lt;/em&gt;’s son is almost always good in calculations and Maths? Why is that? Why doesn’t it tend to behave more like a musician?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Because, the child spends the maximum time with his parents. He sees the kind of work his father does or the daily chores that his mother gets involved it. He might not be paying much attention to all of this throughout his life. But the brain keeps on peeping through. The unconscious learning happens. Or what we call an &lt;strong&gt;unsupervised&lt;/strong&gt; learning in data-science.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In the long run, the best learning happens when it is not enforced. When the child learns on his own, at his own rate.
You want your child to be interested in reading? Make your home a library. Not so fancy or anything. Just surround the room and tables with books. Read it to your baby even when you think the baby doesn’t understand a single word. Let the unsupervised learning happen. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Let the brain enjoy the feel of reading. The idea of living many lives through these books. Every character in these stories will add to the learning. And by the time the child grows, the brain is already hooked to this habit of reading. It has tasted the palatable food of reading. And it can’t survive without it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say, you want him to be a musician. You already know what you need to do.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Do you realize, what have you done by reading out everyday to your child?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
You have introduced a bias in your child’s character. A good bias, I would say. How interesting is that we can relate machine-learning and a child’s learning behaviors. And, we all know what happens to a biased model. It doesn’t work well. There is a &lt;a href="http://scott.fortmann-roe.com/docs/BiasVariance.html"&gt;trade-off&lt;/a&gt; between bias and variance you know.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
While, it’s good to have the child spend time with good people and have a nurtured learning. The child would know about the right things. But don’t stop your child from interacting with someone who is not in your good books. Let us call that someone Asura.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now Asura may not be on good terms with you and you may have legitimate reasons for that. Maybe you feel that Asura is immoral and unscrupulous. But you have seen only a part of Asura’s character. Maybe Asura is an excellent guitar player or a seasoned writer or he could be an expert in other domains. You don’t know.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Let his learning be flexible. Let the bad data be part of his life. Let him enjoy the outliers as well, be it a good or a bad one. With the bad outlier — Asura, make sure you enforce a little of your experience and monitor the child’s learning of good and the evil. Let the supervised learning come into play.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Don’t let your child have limited experiences of just the right things. Don’t limit the datasets in his life or the variance will be huge which again is not a good thing.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Let the learning be both a mix of unsupervised and supervised. A semi-supervised learning we call it in data-science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="learnings"></category><category term="thoughts"></category></entry><entry><title>Shell commands come in handy for a data scientist</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/09/30/shell_commands_for_data_scientist/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-09-30T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-09-30:blog/2016/09/30/shell_commands_for_data_scientist/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am no expert of shell commands. I have been using them for quite some time and thought I give an attempt to list down the most common commands. I am writing these mostly from the perspective of a data-science guy. Let us get started.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I will use the file- ‘data.txt’ to illustrate these commands. ‘data.txt’ is a file having 200 rows and 8 columns. You can access the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ManishBarnwal/LearnNew/blob/master/LearnShellCommands/data.txt"&gt;data&lt;/a&gt; here.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;cat&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Throws the the contents of the entire file at your terminal
    &lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
    &lt;code class="bash"&gt;cat data.txt
    &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
We don’t want to bombard our terminal with the complete content of the file. Instead, if you want to have a complete look at the file, open the file in vim editor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;vim&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Opens the file in the editor  &lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
    &lt;code class="bash"&gt;vim data.txt
    &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;head&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Gives the top 10 rows of the text file at your terminal
    &lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
    &lt;code class="bash"&gt;head data.txt
    &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;tail&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Gives the bottom 10 rows of the text file at your terminal
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="bash"&gt;tail -n 2 data.txt -- This will give you the bottom 2 rows of the file
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The piping operator&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="bash"&gt;cat data.txt | head
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Notice the &lt;strong&gt;|&lt;/strong&gt; operator. This is called pipe operator. Piping is a concept wherein you can perform a sequence of operations in a single command.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So what exactly is piping?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pipe is a facility of the shell that makes it easy to chain together multiple commands. When used between two Unix commands, it means that output from the first command should become the input to the second command. Just read the &lt;strong&gt;|&lt;/strong&gt; in the command as &lt;em&gt;pass the data onto&lt;/em&gt;. More on this operator later in the post.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;wc&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;wc&lt;/strong&gt; is a fairly useful shell command that lets you count the number of lines(-l), words(-w) or characters(-c) in a given file
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="bash"&gt;wc -l data.txt -- gives you the number of lines in the file
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="bash"&gt;wc -w data.txt -- gives you the number of words in the file
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;wc -c data.txt -- gives you the number of characters in the file
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;head -n 1 data.txt| wc -w -- gives you the number of columns in the file
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;grep&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider ‘grep’ as a command to filter on the results you get. You may want to print all the lines in your file which have a particular phrase. Say for example you want to see people who are ‘Very Happy’. You simply pass this to grep command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;grep 'Very Happy' data.txt | head
-- gives you the top 10 rows having 'Very Happy'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us say, we want to count the number of users who are ‘Not Happy’
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;grep 'Not Happy' data.txt | wc -l
-- gives you the top 10 rows having 'Very Happy'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;sort&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to sort the data based on some column, say ‘Score’; ‘Score’ is the 3rd column in the file- data.txt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;sort -t ',' -k 3 -n -r data.txt |head -5
-- gives you the top 10 rows having 'Very Happy'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation: -t is used to specify the delimiter; ‘,’ in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the delimiter is ‘\t’, we don’t need to specify -t argument. Space is taken as delimiter by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;k is used to specify the column based on which you want to sort the data; 3 in this case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;n is to specify that sorting is to be done numerically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;r is to imply that the sorting is descending
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;cut&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This command gives you only specific column. Say you want to see only the 4th column of the file.
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;cut data.txt -d ',' -f 4 |head
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Explanation: ‘,’ is the delimiter. 4 is the column number that you want to see.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;uniq&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not confuse this command for ‘unique’. It is slightly different. This &lt;strong&gt;removes sequential duplicates&lt;/strong&gt;.
So if you want to get unique values from a column, you need to first sort the data and then use this &lt;em&gt;uniq&lt;/em&gt; command in sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get the unique of a column, say the 2nd column
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;cut data.txt -d ',' -f 2 |sort|uniq
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
This command could be used with argument -c to count the occurrence of these distinct values. Something like to count distinct in SQL.
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;cut data.txt -d ',' -f 2 |sort|uniq-c
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;tr&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &lt;strong&gt;tr&lt;/strong&gt; stands for translate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Find and Replace’ function that we have in excel. Yes we have that in UNIX as well.
A typical use of this command that I use on regular basis is that I get the file from HIVE which are tab delimited. And say I want to convert it to ‘,’ delimited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also want to replace certain characters in file with something else using the &lt;em&gt;tr&lt;/em&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;cat data.txt | tr ',' '\t'  -- Changed ',' delimited to '\t' delimited
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Save to a new file or append to an existing file&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/strong&gt; operator
Say you want to save the output of operations to some file. You use ‘&amp;gt;’ or ‘&amp;gt;&amp;gt;’ depending on whether you want it to be a new file or you want to append it to an existing file.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I will update this list as and when I see a command deserving enough to be in a data scientist’s toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts on the topic in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="shell-commands"></category></entry><entry><title>ROC and AUC - The three lettered acronyms</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/09/26/three_letter_acronym_roc_and_auc/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-09-26T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-09-26:blog/2016/09/26/three_letter_acronym_roc_and_auc/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don't feel bad to confess this that &lt;em&gt;ROC curve&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;AUC&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;True-positive&lt;/em&gt; and related terms took quite some time for me to understand. If today I contemplate on the reasons why I found this topic confusing. The first would be there are not many resources that explains intuitively what these mean. They just jump to the terms and the mathematical formula for them. The second being I had not used them even in my project work. You see the project work is never enough for all your learnings.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In this post, I will try to explain my understanding both intuitively and mathematically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will illustrate this concept with the help of an example.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
There is a bank say &lt;em&gt;SBI&lt;/em&gt; that wants to understand which of its future customers would default on a loan granted by the bank. The bank would already have historical data from the past years that says how many of the customers have defaulted, what type of customer were they and many other information about the past loans.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It is very rare that customers default. To give an example, say the bank has data having 1000 rows that contains information like &lt;em&gt;age&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;gender&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;income&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;marital-status&lt;/em&gt;, other related columns and then a variable named &lt;em&gt;default&lt;/em&gt; that says whether the customer has defaulted or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned earlier, very few customers default on their loans. So a realistic example would be say 100 customers defaulting out of a total of 1000 customers.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The bank is interested in knowing if a customer would default or not. This is a typical binary classification problem. The bank would really be interested in the customers who are likely to default. Let us now try to understand terms like &lt;em&gt;True-positive&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;True-negative&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;False-positive&lt;/em&gt; and other related terms.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
There are two levels in the &lt;em&gt;default&lt;/em&gt; variable that we are trying to predict-&lt;strong&gt;default&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;not-default&lt;/strong&gt;. One has to define first whether &lt;strong&gt;default&lt;/strong&gt; will be treated as positive or &lt;strong&gt;not-default&lt;/strong&gt; as positive. It is just a convention. Normally, the class of interest is treated as positive. So in the bank's case, what do you think we should take as positive? You might have guessed it correctly, we will treat &lt;strong&gt;default&lt;/strong&gt; as positive and &lt;strong&gt;not-default&lt;/strong&gt; as negative.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
We train a binary classification model on this dataset having 1000 rows. The predictions that the model makes for the training data will either be correct or incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There will be two cases for incorrect predictions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predicting positive when the actual was negative i.e classifying a customer as default when in actual he is not-default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predicting negative when the actual was positive i.e classifying a customer as not-default when in actual he is default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There will be two cases for correct predictions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predicting positive when the actual was positive i.e correctly classifying default as default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predicting negative when the actual was negative i.e correctly classifying not-default as not-default
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now, FP, FN are incorrect predictions (notice False in the name) as the name suggests and TP, TN are the correct predictions. Don't be in a hurry here. Take some time to digest these 2 lettered acronyms. Read them loud. Take a notebook and write them down on your own.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Once we are comfortable with these terms we will discuss about something called confusion-matrix. Don't get confused yet. If you understood TP, TN, FP, FN then confusion-matrix is just a matrix having these values. The diagonal elements contain the count of correct predictions (TP, TN) whereas the off-diagonal contain the count of incorrect predictions (FP, FN). The rows are the predicted and the columns are the actual.
This looks something like this.
&lt;Insert a picture&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why we need TPR, FPR if we already have mis-classification error?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data I describe above is a typical case of imbalanced data wherein one of the class is having majority of observations (90% non-defaulters (negatives) in our data) and the remaining class is a minority (only 10% defaulters (positives)). In such cases, the predictions on new dataset will be skewed towards negatives i.e the model will classify a lot of defaulters (positives) into negatives. The bank can't afford to have such predictions. The bank wants to know for sure the defaulters (positives). Imagine, the loss to bank if the model classify a probable defaulter (positive) to non-defaulter.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In such cases, accuracy corresponding to mis-classification alone is not acceptable. The bank would be more interested in correctly classifying the positives into positive i.e the bank wants to classify the defaulters into defaulters without fail.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Comes into picture &lt;em&gt;TPR&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TNR&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;FPR&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;FNR&lt;/em&gt;. These 3 lettered acronyms are nothing but the rates of TP, TN, FP and FN respectively.
Below is the formula. To digest the formula, let's move to our data having 1000 rows - 100 defaulters (positives) and 900 non-defaulters(negatives). Suppose we employed a logistic regression that classified 80 defaulters correctly and incorrectly classified 90 non-defaulters as defaulters.
TPR = 80 / 100 = 0.8
FPR = 90/ 900 = 0.1
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How does the TPR and FPR gets calculated?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever you do any classification, the model always gives you probabilities of each observation getting classified in each of the classes.
Based on what cut-off you choose, you will get different predictions for the data and hence different TPR and FPR overall. You can choose whatever probability cut-off between [0, 1] and you will get different tuples of TPR and FPR.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TPR and FPR are be generated for each of the probability value one chooses. And these values are then plotted on an ROC curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
One can plot these tuples (probability, FPR, TPR) on a graph. You know what this graph is called? ROC-Receiver Operating Characteristics.
There is a trade-off between TPR and FPR. Depending on the requirement one can choose the probability cut-off that best fulfills their purpose. For instance, in the bank's case, the bank wants to not miss a single defaulter(positives) i.e the bank wants a higher TPR. The ROC curve looks something like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, all this is clear to me.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What about AUC?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AUC is nothing but the area under curve of ROC curve. Let's say we built a logistic regression model that gave us the probabilities for each row. Now we try with probability cut-offs from 0.1 to 1.0 with step size of 0.1 i.e we would have 10 probabilites to try with and corresponding to each of the 10 values we would have corresponding (FPR, TPR). If we plot these values on a graph we would get a graph having 10 points. This 10 point graph is what we call an ROC curve and the area under this graph is called AUC.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The AUC is a common evaluation metric for binary classification problems. Consider a plot of the true positive rate vs the false positive rate as the threshold value for classifying an item as 0 or is increased from 0 to 1: if the classifier is very good, the true positive rate will increase quickly and the area under the curve will be close to 1. If the classifier is no better than random guessing, the true positive rate will increase linearly with the false positive rate and the area under the curve will be around 0.5.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
One characteristic of the AUC is that it is independent of the fraction of the test population which is class 0 or class 1: this makes the AUC useful for evaluating the performance of classifiers on unbalanced data sets.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The larger the area the better. If we have to choose between two classifiers having different AUCs, we choose the one having larger AUC.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do you decide what probability cut-off should you choose to classify them into either of the classes?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some say they take a cut-off of 0.5 i.e observation having probability greater than 0.5 will be classified as positive or else negative. Do you see the problem in here? Try thinking.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Come into picture ROC curve. Look at the ROC curve and depending on what value of TPR or FPR you want from your model, you take probability corresponding to that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ROC, AUC can easily be plotted and calculated using modern analytical tools like R or Python. But I would suggest for better understanding of this topic, try writing your own code.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I will make an attempt of the same soon and will share it on this space. Keep learning and sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts on the topic in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="roc"></category><category term="auc"></category></entry><entry><title>Vim/Vi editor shortcuts</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/09/22/vim_shortcuts/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-09-22T04:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-09-22:blog/2016/09/22/vim_shortcuts/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Repetitive tasks should be done using as many shortcuts as possible. You are not doing  anything new and hence not even an extra minute should be spent on doing the same. This post refers to the shortcuts that come in handy when working on the vi/vim editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not an exhaustive list. These are the ones I use frequently. Feel free to comment down your favorite shortcuts.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Navigation keys&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Moves cursor to the start of the line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Moves cursor to the end of the line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;w&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Moves forward one word&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;b&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Moves backward one word&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;G&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Moves to the end of the file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 + G&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Moves to the beginning of file
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Delete text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dw&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Deletes a word ahead of the cursor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;db&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Deletes a word behind the cursor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;d0&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Deletes the complete line till beginning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;d$&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Deletes the complete line till the end&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dd&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Deletes the complete line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10dd&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Deletes the following 5 lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dG&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Deletes till the end of the file
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Undo/Redo operation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;u&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Undo the last operation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ctrl + r&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Redo the last undo
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Search and Replace keys&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;/search_text&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Finds 'search_text' in file going forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;?search_text&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Finds 'search_text' in file going backward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Finds the next occurrence of 'search_text'&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Finds the previous occurrence of 'search_text'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:%s/replace_what/replace_with&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Replaces first occurrence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:%s/replace_what/replace_with/g&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Replaces all occurrences globally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:%s/replace_what/replace_with/c&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Asks for confirmation
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Save and quit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:q!&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Force quit without saving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:wq&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Saves the changes made to the document&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:wq!&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Forcefully saves the changes made to the document&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:w new_file_name&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Saves the file to a new file named new_file_name
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Command line shortcuts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ctrl + a&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Brings to the beginning of the line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ctrl + e&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   Brings to the end of the line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="vi/vim"></category></entry><entry><title>Hadoop Streaming</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/08/29/hadoop_streaming/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-08-29T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-08-29:blog/2016/08/29/hadoop_streaming/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I had written a post on &lt;strong&gt;The Big Data Problem&lt;/strong&gt; which attempted to understand why we need big data and what the fuss is all about. You may want to read it &lt;a href="http://manishbarnwal.com/blog/2016/06/29/big_data_problem/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Having understood why we need big data, let’s understand how we can go about analyzing the same. What is the way out to do analysis on big data? The solution is Streaming…Hadoop Streaming. &lt;em&gt;James Bond style&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
To recount a personal experience, I was faced with the following Data Analysis task — Scaling a particular analytics technique on retail data from one store to all stores across the US. Sounds interesting so far, doesn’t it? The catch however, was that the program took 2 days just to compute the results for 1 department.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Imagine, the time it would take if we were restricted to a single machine/Rstudio.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Let’s understand the gravity of the problem and get an idea of a rough time estimate. 
So for one department the time taken was two days. Let us assume, each store has close to 100 departments and we have a total of 5000 stores. So the total time taken for all of the stores would be roughly 2 X 100 X 5000 = 1 million days = 2740 years. This is just a rough estimate assuming a linear relationship between the number of departments and the time taken.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Obviously, using RStudio stand alone was not a feasible solution. We had at our disposal Hadoop cluster. We wanted to see if we could exploit the number of machines in our cluster to solve this Herculean challenge of the Big Data world.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
A fresh college graduate, I was a complete stranger to the world of Hadoop and out of anxiety, I purchased a copy of &lt;em&gt;Hadoop-The definitive guide&lt;/em&gt;. I started going through the chapters. It was in no time that I realized this book was meant for someone with an understanding of Java. Unfortunately, I was not one of them. Saddened and almost defeated. What other choice do I have? I came across this wonderful concept — Hadoop streaming.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Wow! This looks like it could solve the problem. I started reading more about it on the internet. There were not many resources on this technique. Fortunately, a colleague of mine had worked on Hadoop Streaming earlier and with his help we were able to accomplish the task successfully.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now that you have the context, let me try to answer some basic technical questions.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So what exactly is Hadoop streaming?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadoop streaming — ‘hadoop’ and ‘streaming’. We use the availability of machines in the cluster to process data in parallel. Let me elaborate. When we do our analysis on Rstudio, we just have one machine (our laptop). Now imagine we have 100s of such machines in our cluster. We can take advantage of this and distribute our input data in such a way that each machine gets some portion of your input data and they are processed in parallel.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Now, you may ask what is streaming here.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The input data is sent to each of the machines in the cluster via stdin() (standard input) and the analyzed output is thrown at stdout() (standard output). Your input data is streamed via stdin and the output gets flushed out to stdout.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What languages can I use for Hadoop streaming?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use any scripting language — R, Python, Ruby. Care should be taken to choose your scripting language. The analysis you are planning to do on your data should decide your choice of language. Say, we want to do a forecasting of sales at item level for a retail store. We know that R is the suitable choice to use when it comes to do forecasting as we have well-developed packages in R which is not the case with Ruby. So do put some thought into choosing the language.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I hope we are now clear on the basics of Hadoop Streaming and its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadoop Streaming is not the answer to all your Big Data analysis problems. It can be used only for cases where each machine can independently perform its analysis with a small portion of input data that is fed to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example where Hadoop Streaming can be used&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sales forecasting at item level. Say, we have weekly data for 2 years at item level. And say there are 10,000 items for which we want to do the forecasting. Each item has close to 104 rows (2 years weekly data). So our input data has close to 104 X 10,000 = 1,040,000 ~ 1 million rows. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Assume we have 100 machines in our cluster. What we do next is pretty intuitive. We distribute our data such that each machine receives 1 item at a time, and once it is done processing that item, we send the next item to it. So, in a single go, we will have 100 items processed across the cluster. In, the next go, again more 100 items will be processed and this goes on until all the 10,000 items are processed.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example where Hadoop Streaming won’t work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-means_clustering"&gt;Clustering&lt;/a&gt;. In clustering we need to find the hidden patterns that are there in the complete dataset. A smaller portion of the dataset can’t be sent to a machine to do the analysis because the purpose will not be served.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I think this is worth mentioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hadoop Streaming, you are not writing an &lt;strong&gt;org.apache.hadoop.mapred.Mapper class&lt;/strong&gt;! This is just a simple script that reads rows from stdin (columns separated by ‘\t’ or any delimiter) and should write rows to stdout (again, columns separated by ‘\t’ or other delimiter). It’s probably worth mentioning this again but you shouldn’t be thinking in traditional map-reduce &lt;strong&gt;Key Value&lt;/strong&gt; terms, you need to think about columns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
You can write your script in any language you want, but it needs to be available on all machines in the cluster. Any easy way to do this is to take advantage of the Hadoop &lt;strong&gt;distributed cache support&lt;/strong&gt;, and just use add file /path/to/script within hive. The script will then be distributed and can be run as just ./script (assuming it is executable)
Enough theoretical stuff. The interesting part is the code framework of mapper and reducer that I will explain in the next post. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I hope you feel more educated on big data after reading this. Please leave a comment if you have questions/insights. I will reply as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="big data"></category><category term="analytics"></category><category term="hadoop"></category></entry><entry><title>When R package is not available across the cluster</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/08/02/r_packages_not_in_cluster/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-08-02T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-08-02:blog/2016/08/02/r_packages_not_in_cluster/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When deploying R codes across the cluster, many a times the reason for the failure of the task is unavailability of a particular package across all nodes of the cluster. We wait for someone to get the package installed across all the nodes. This may take some days. Do we wait for them? &lt;em&gt;Naah!&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Presenting a temporary solution that one of my colleague came up with. I have used this technique and this works smoothly.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The following are the steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the package you require on one of the edge nodes into a local directory&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a local directory. Let's say our directory name is &lt;em&gt;rPackages&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
    &lt;code class="bash"&gt;mkdir rPackages
    &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the required package, say 'randomForest' in the directory just created
    &lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
    &lt;code class="r"&gt;install.packages('randomForest', repos=’repo_name', lib='rPackages/')
    Note that you need to choose the appropriate repo_name. The one that your company allows.
    &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
2. Check if you can load the package from this local directory
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="r"&gt;library(randomForest, lib.loc='rPackages/')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
3. Create zip file of “dir_location” using command
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="bash"&gt;zip -r rPackages.zip rPackages/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
4. Add this zip file in your HIVE hql (or anything else)
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="bash"&gt;add file rPackages.zip;
Don’t forget the semicolon
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
5. Unzip the file inside R script i.e. each reducer will have &lt;em&gt;rPackages&lt;/em&gt; directory now
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="bash"&gt;unzip('rPackages.zip', overwrite=TRUE)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
6. Load the package now
&lt;pre style="font-size:60%; padding:7px; margin:0em;"&gt;
&lt;code class="bash"&gt;library(randomForest, lib.loc='rPackages/')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you’re done! Remember, you have to build the package where you want to use, because built packages are OS dependent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="big data"></category><category term="R"></category></entry><entry><title>The most inspiring talk I ever attended live</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/07/26/the_most_inspiring_talk_live/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-07-26T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-07-26:blog/2016/07/26/the_most_inspiring_talk_live/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/walmartlabs-india"&gt;WalmartLabs&lt;/a&gt; India was one of the sponsors of IIT Bombay’s alumni meet and I along with few of my colleagues got a chance to attend the meet-up. I didn’t have much idea about the speakers who were going to present. All I knew was, we wanted to get some good talent for our company and we had set up a booth where we were presenting the work we do at WalmartLabs.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Of all the speakers that presented their talk, one was mesmerizing. I was impressed by this speaker. The way he confidently took the stage. Stood casually by the dais. He didn’t carry any presentation with him unlike the other speakers. There was a charm and calmness in his presence. It was as if he knew that we were eagerly waiting to hear him out.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
He introduced himself as &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ravi-venkatesan-ba15b820"&gt;Ravi Venkatesan&lt;/a&gt;. He gave a brief background about his college, the works he had done, and the great experiences he had in his career of 30 years. Nothing unusual or impressive so far. But when he mentioned the different fields in which he had done his work, I was awestruck. I was not able to digest the fact that he had worked as someone who established Microsoft in India during its early years after having manufactured engines in his previous job. See the difference in the two kinds of work.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Many had asked him not to take this job at Microsoft. That it was not safe to make such a change from working on engines to IT sector. Even his most trusted mentors were not in favor of this change. But this guy wanted to wear this new hat and take this risk. Not to prove anyone wrong but to ensure that later in his life he never had the guilt of not trying.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People generally don’t try new things because they fear the idea of failing. The moment one conquers this feeling and see beyond…all one can see is opportunity, learning, and experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
He was in no hurry to finish up his talk. Slowly, he went on describing his journey of ups-and-downs. His talk was mostly on advices on career.
I remember him mentioning this.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The age of 40 is a magical year. Once you reach this, you start getting serious. You have in front of you, the 40 years you have already lived, you have the list of things you wanted to accomplish, and the things you have actually conquered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next thought that comes to your mind is you don’t have much time left. A few more years and your career will come to a halt. In the next few years, you would like to get the most out of your life. Do not wait to reach this magical year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do things you want to do NOW. Get out of your comfort zone. Take risks. His words were powerful and convincing.
Another anecdote from his life. He had applied for Harvard just after graduating from IIT Bombay. Sadly, he was rejected. Dejected and shattered, he called upon the office asking why was he rejected?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The person on the other side replied — &lt;em&gt;you don’t have anything different&lt;/em&gt;. Your grades are good and all but how are you different? He had no answer.
Few years passed by. Ravi liked reading about various things. He started writing about these things. His interest towards writing increased exponentially and fortunately at the age of 26, he became the youngest man to have his article published in the &lt;strong&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/strong&gt;. Obviously, he got admitted to Harvard the next time.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
My eyes glistened with awe.
Here was a guy who had not given up. He continued doing things he liked and gave an answer to how he was different from others.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The auditorium echoed with claps from the audience. The speaker opened up for questions from the audience which he patiently answered. There were many in the audience who had more questions to be answered. Time was running short and he had to leave the stage for the next speaker to come.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Did you find the post useful? If you did, share your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="career"></category></entry><entry><title>The Big Data Problem</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/06/29/big_data_problem/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-29T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-06-29:blog/2016/06/29/big_data_problem/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big data&lt;/strong&gt; has become a sensation these days. Anyone and everyone wants to use this in their discussions. When I was still in my college and preparing for campus placements, I had attended almost all the pre-placement talks that companies gave to its prospective candidates.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
American Express was one such company that had talked extensively about big data and hadoop in their presentation. I remember clearly, the blank faces that all of us had. We were not able to follow a single term. &lt;strong&gt;Hadoop&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;clusters&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;big data&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;distributed environment&lt;/strong&gt; and many other terms were just bouncers for me. I did try to google them up later but these terms were still alien to me.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I have worked at WalmartLabs for close to 2 years now and the work has mostly been on the big data side. Walmart is one of the largest companies when it comes to capturing the transactions data that we have on daily basis both at the stores and at the e-commerce. Having worked on the big data technologies a little, I felt I would give it a try to make big data and related questions a little easy to understand.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Following are few of the questions that I will try to explain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is Big Data? And why should I care about it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the problem with a single laptop?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a cluster?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The data is distributed across the cluster&lt;/em&gt;. What is meant by this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is Hadoop and Spark?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Everyone is generating data. Data is the side-product of any work we do. &lt;em&gt;Just like smoke is emitted when things burn, data is created when machines work or interact with each other&lt;/em&gt;. These machines used to emit data in the past as well, but we were not advanced enough to collect the data. The technologies weren’t capable of capturing these.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Today, every other thing is emitting data. Be it the signals from your refrigerator, the air-conditioners in your room, the cars on the street, the videos that you like or dislike on YouTube, your transactions at the nearby Super-market, the posts you make on Facebook. These are all emissions of your day-to-day work.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Companies and analysts want to understand you and your behavior using the data you generate. To give you an idea of how much data is generated, let’s look at the ridiculous amount of data some of the big giants produce on daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook’s daily logs are more than &lt;strong&gt;60 terabytes&lt;/strong&gt; every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google’s web index is more than &lt;strong&gt;10 petabytes&lt;/strong&gt; of information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Millions of customers visit Walmart stores on daily basis. Imagine the &lt;strong&gt;size of these transactions data&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we need this data? Of course!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every data has a story. With proper analysis and techniques, we can get a lot from data. Now, there will be times when you won’t get anything insightful from it. I consider this also good. Maybe, there is something wrong with the way we are collecting the data and we need to have a look at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So far we know that every other thing is puking data. And they are puking in bulk. To get something good out of these pukes, we need to store them somewhere, do our analysis on them and get insights. How do we go about it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storage of this data has never been a problem. The disks are relatively cheap. A terabyte of disk costs ~ $35. So storing them on physical disks is not an issue. What is the problem then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you have an idea how fast the data can be read from a disk? It is still in Mbs/sec. Let us assume a speed of 100 Mbs/sec. With this speed, the time taken to read 1 terabyte of data would be ~ 3 hours! Below is the calculation for 3 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 terabytes = 1000,000 Mb. So the total time ~ 1000,000/100 ~ 10000 seconds ~ 10000/3600 ~ 3 hours&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 hours is too huge a time to read 1 terabyte of data given the amount of data giants like Facebook generates on daily basis. Also, a single machine won’t be able to handle this much data. So what is the solution?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
What if we could distribute the data across multiple machines? Yes, that sounds promising. The data that is big enough to handle by one machine can be distributed across multiple machines such that each machine has some portion of the actual data. Now these machines are interconnected with each other and so there is no issue of interactions between these machines. And that is exactly what a cluster is.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
A &lt;em&gt;cluster&lt;/em&gt; is a combination of many machines connected to each other. Think of it like this. There is a process by which, my computer and your computer can be connected to each other and we can have a cluster with two nodes or machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, that you have your machines connected with each other in the cluster, you can take advantage of the computation power of each of the machines. And thus, the task which one couldn’t even think of accomplishing by a single machine can now be very easily be done by a cluster of machines.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is hadoop and Spark? And how are they different?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadoop is a framework that supports the storage and processing of large data sets in a distributed computing environment.It provides massive storage for any kind of data, enormous processing power and the ability to handle virtually limitless concurrent tasks or jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spark is a powerful analytics engine. It is a fast and general engine for large-scale data processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadoop provides both the data storage and processing power whereas Spark is meant for doing analysis and processing of big data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to notice is, Spark is about 10 to 100 times faster than the Hadoop MapReduce framework by making use of in-memory processing compared to persistence storage used by Hadoop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spark is a Swiss army knife of analytics world&lt;/em&gt;. There are various APIs- Python, R, Scala thorough which one can interact with the Spark framework. For machine learning algorithms, there is MlLib which can be used to perform some common analysis like regression, K-means clustering, and classification.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
We will talk more about Spark in future posts. I am exploring it rigorously and plan to write out my understanding of it soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed reading this post and feel a little more familiar with big data now. Hit the share button if you would like your friends to read this.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="big data"></category><category term="analytics"></category><category term="hadoop"></category><category term="spark"></category></entry><entry><title>My first attempt at public speaking</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/06/27/first_attempt_at_public%20speaking/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-27T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-06-27:blog/2016/06/27/first_attempt_at_public speaking/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having graduated from college, it was just 6 months into my new job that I was asked to give a tech-talk on &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Data Science&lt;/em&gt;. Imagine the thrill and fright of a fresher when he is presented with a situation like this. The first thing I asked my manager was — how many people are we expecting in the audience? Notice the fright in the question. I was scared that I might screw up in front of a large audience. I may not be able to present the talk eloquently, the audience may laugh at me and all those crappy thoughts that quickly clouds your mind with fear and uncertainty.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Without much thought and ignoring the above questions, I straight away agreed to present the talk. &lt;strong&gt;The plan was simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Commit to the task and then learn how to do it. In a few days, after a lot many iterations I had the presentation ready with me. I had not prepared any script or dialogues for the talk. The reason being, I wanted to give an impromptu talk. Days passed and I got busy in routine office work and meeting project deadlines.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Writing and public-speaking was something that has always fascinated me. I had read many a posts on effective public-speaking. Now was the time to apply whatever I had read about it.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The day had come when I had to give the tech-talk. That morning, I woke up a little early and I looked at a few videos on dealing with the stage-fear. I found this video in particular to be helpful.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It’s not that I had not practiced at all. We had a few dry runs. Frankly, I didn’t had the exact lines that I intended to say. I had just planned the overall flow of the talk. As I had read on various blogs on public-speaking, I reached the conference room a little early, walked down the room confidently, talked to some of my colleagues about random topics so as to divert the attention and calm the nerves. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Within a few minutes, the room got packed with folks from various teams. I hadn’t expected these many people to turn around. Nevertheless, I was happy and confident. I kept saying this to myself — &lt;em&gt;you are going to rock today! So many people have come just to listen to you. You know this stuff. This is your bread and butter&lt;/em&gt;. I took a few deep breaths and started the talk. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
After first few minutes of the talk, I started reading some of the faces in the audience, trying to understand if they are following what was being spoken. A good proxy for this include people asking questions, nodding to your statements in agreement, and making notes. I could see the audience doing these. So the feedback was good and I continued with the talk.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It was not all that easy. I stammered in between, fell short of the right words, the throat felt thirsty, some of the faces in audience looked scary but somehow the confidence in me was at peak. &lt;strong&gt;I was happy talking about something that I enjoyed doing&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It has been almost a year since I had presented this talk. Now when I think about it, I feel good. I feel accomplished. I know I could have screwed up badly. I had to start somewhere. And today I am happy that I did take that chance.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Next time, don’t let that chance pass away. Take that risk, prepare well and make it your first attempt at public speaking. We all need to start somewhere.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category></entry><entry><title>Understanding HIVE for data science people</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/06/22/understanding_hive_data_science/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-22T04:43:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-06-22:blog/2016/06/22/understanding_hive_data_science/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been working as Statistical analyst for the last 1.5 years and fortunately I got to work on Hadoop on one of my initial projects. Hadoop sounds scary to a lot of people and I am no exception. In this post, I would make an attempt to explain HIVE-the data warehouse for Hadoop ecosystem. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is HIVE? And why as an analyst I should care about it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HIVE is the part of the Hadoop infrastructure where data gets stored and you can write your query to fetch data from HIVE (tables). Now when I had started working on Hadoop, I knew a little SQL and a tad little of data science. I had take a few courses on Statistics during my college but then who really studies in college! Having allocated to a project which required an understanding of Hadoop, I planned how I need to understand this system so that I can contribute my best to the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing you need to build any model is data. Comes to picture-HIVE. As I said, I knew SQL and as I started working on HIVE I got to know that if one knows SQL then one knows HIVE, it’s just that he is not aware of it yet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I say so? 
Because, HIVE was built with the sole purpose that database people who are comfortable working on SQL need not require to learn a completely new language to fetch and interact with data in the Hadoop ecosystem. And I believe the founders of Hadoop have achieved this successfully. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HIVE hides the map-reduce processes from the user and all you need to worry about is writing your SQL query. You don’t need to worry at all about mappers and reducers. All these information is hidden from the user and if one wants to know more on these, there are ways to know that as well (advanced users of HIVE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will cover most common queries that we deal with when working as an analyst on Hadoop- creating a table (external/internal), getting information about table, setting common HIVE settings and a few others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a table
Table in HIVE can be of 2 types: Internal or External
Stay with me for next few lines and I will explain the differences. 
By default, the table that we create in most of the cases is internal table. However, external tables come into picture when you want to build a table over some file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between external and internal table is in terms of what happens when we drop a table. 
External table:
 —  If you drop the table, the table and the metadata of the data is dropped but not the data 
 The data is located in hdfs (and not in local file system) and since this data is accessed by many tables we don’t want the data to get dropped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just add the keyword external to specify that we want to build an external table.
 —  CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE external_table_name&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internal table:
 —  If you drop the table, the table, metadata and even the data is dropped
 —  If the data for the table resides in the local file system, you should go for creating internal table&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—  CREATE INTERNAL TABLE internal_table or just CREATE TABLE internal_table
Once the table gets created, we want to get the data from the table for our analysis. Before we dive into getting the data from the table, it is a good idea to get an idea about the overall structure of the table — column names, column types, whether external or internal, owner of the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these information can be retrieved by using this: describe formatted table_name; This gives you a lot of information in a formatted manner. If you are in a hurry and just want to see the column names and no other details, use desc table_name;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;External tables are created over some file. This file should be located in hdfs-file system for hadoop. A few command lines would easily move the file to hdfs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How to move a file to hdfs?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are the steps:
- Create a directory where you want to move the file
  hadoop fs -mkdir directory_name
- Check if the directory got created
  hadoop fs -ls ; you should see your directory name here
  This directory is empty right now. You can check this using
  hadoop fs -ls directory_name; It's empty
- Move the file from local to hdfs
  hadoop fs -copyFromLocal 'path where file is stored' directory_name
- Check if the file has been copied to directory
  hadoop fs -ls directory_name; You should see the file now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open vim editor and write the below codes in any file. I will name my file create_table.hql
vim create_table.hql
Creating table. Code below&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;drop external table if exists db_name.table_name;
create external table if not exists db_name.table_name (
ID    string,
WorkStatus     string,
Score    int,
Residence_Region    string,
income    string,
Gender    smallint,
Alcohol_Consumption    string,
Happy    string
)
row format delimited
fields terminated by ‘\t’
stored as textfile
location ‘/user/mbarnwa/data1’
;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dropping a database
Many a times, you may want to drop a database that you don’t need anymore. Say, the database to be dropped is ‘userdb’, then if you do this: drop database userdb; 
Now the above command will work if your database is empty i.e. the database, ‘userdb’ has no tables in it. 
But that is rarely a case, so either you can go ahead on deleting each table in the database by using this command drop table ‘tableName’; or addition of a simple keyword — CASCADE will solve your purpose. So the final command to drop a database (even if it has tables) is 
drop database ‘userdb’ cascade;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Hive"></category><category term="hadoop"></category><category term="big data"></category></entry><entry><title>Pre-Placement Talk Snippets</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/09/07/pre-placement_talk_snippets/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-07T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-09-07:blog/2014/09/07/pre-placement_talk_snippets/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'd attended &lt;em&gt;PPTs&lt;/em&gt; (Pre-placement Talks) of almost all the companies I'd interest in during my placement time. Many students find attending PPTs a waste of time. I was not one of them.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I liked attending PPTs. I felt they gave me continuous motivation to be consistent in my preparation. I remember the first PPT I'd attended. It was EXL and it felt like almost every final year student was in that room. Not a single chair in &lt;em&gt;Kalidas Auditorium&lt;/em&gt; was unoccupied.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Looking at such a big crowd of students in that auditorium, me and my friend looked at each other with confused looks. We exchanged these words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me: "Yaar Rahul, yaha toh bahot log hai be. Competition tagda hai be."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rahul: "Ho jaaega be. Naukri hi toh hai."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes the competition is going to be tough. So be prepared. I'm not trying to scare you. I'm just saying give your best shot at preparing for the companies you're interested in. It's just a matter of few months. I remember I'd studied more in that semester than all the previous semesters combined. This semester is an opportunity to learn the maximum out of your college life. Make it count.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I always made it a practice to take notes of the presentations I was attending. And then when needed I would look at them and try to understand what exactly is the company looking for. Be the boring one and take notes.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Following are the snippets of some of the companies I could find in my mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FICo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define score card for banking and lending institutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clients include DB, HSBC, ICICI bank, Coca-Cola, JP Morgan Chase, Healthways&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Project in diverse fields&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FiCo score - Number 1 score in North America&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiring 25 to 30 people across India&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Custom analytic modeling for Maths and Computing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Informal structure and informal culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miebach consulting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supply chain Company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is supply chain - Everything involving from the start of manufacture of product till delivery at right time at right price&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started in 1973, started in India in 1996, FOUNDED by Dr. Miebach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consulting in automotive, spare parts, fashion, FMCG, retail and          e-commerce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiring for Associate consultant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close to 60 employees in India&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to be a team player, result oriented, a leader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Procedure for hiring: CV submission, test, GD/case interview&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test quantitative, analytical&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capital one&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Credit cards, auto finance, home loans, consumer and commercial banking...50 percent bigger than SBI in terms of bank labs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Us, UK, Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fortune 500 company, ranked 127&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only 22 years old but is comparable to top banks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Credit card interest rate in India? Look for it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making decisions based on data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Times internet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PLP, product leader program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analytical ability, General aptitude&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic aptitude test followed by pseudo algorithm test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goldman Sachs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Market maker, provides liquidity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advisory services eg. Merger and acquisition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financier eg. For a growing company like Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asset manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Principal, find the best companies to be invested in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Founded in 1869, 32400 people in 65 offices in 34 countries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Survived 2008 crisis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial holding company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bangalore is global hub of GS with representatives from all divisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our client's interests always come first&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We anticipate the rapidly changing needs of our clients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GS culture:   Excellence, integrity team work, meritocracy, entrepreneurial spirit client device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantitative roles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investment management, automated trading, developing algorithms to run trade on electronic markets like NYSE, NASDAQ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Risk modeling building models to quantify market risk, liquidity risk. Post trade activities, surveillance analytics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is risk? Why measure risk? Relevant to whom?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One possible measure: How much can we loose in one day?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historical simulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value at risk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AmEx, American Express&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started in 1850 as courier firm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved to charge and credit card business in 1958&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transactions worth 900 billion dollars by volume globally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interesting projects like shopping through Twitter, tweet to buy launched in US last year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AmEx is all three parties combined in online transaction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;500 plus people based in Gurgaon and Bangalore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decision sciences, campaign management, big data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Newly involved in e-commerce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate different kinds of score&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wipro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wipro, applying thought&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WIPRO: western India vegetable products limited&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got Listed on NYSE in 2001&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provider of Consulting services, BPO, IT, R&amp;amp;D services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Largest independent R&amp;amp;D services provider in the world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six strategic SBU (small business units)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banking &amp;amp; financial services: healthcare, life science and services, retail consumer products, global media &amp;amp; telecom, energy natural resources &amp;amp; utilities, manufacturing and hi-tech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the most ethical companies by Ethisphere institute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Futures First&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Propriety trading, most challenging work in financial services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don't take calls from clients...you invest on your own&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GHF group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trading...buy low, sell high...having an expectation and trying to trade on that expectation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discipline, risk taking ability, decision making, street smartness, flexibility and adaptability, mental toughness, analytical ability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trades in: Interest rates, commodities, foreign exchange, equity index futures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In terms of volume based market share, we are in top 10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group of 700 trader and analysts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started in 1993 in London, in India in 2004&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance bonus on an average of 1.2 lakhs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bonus can be zero or explode to multiple times of your salary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work week from Monday to Friday, working hours depend on your product market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best part is "even I don't know what is the maximum amount I can make" - one of the employees in the video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citi Bank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PPT. presented by Raj Kurucheti&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Global bank, 200 years of history&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader in the financial sector with presence globally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our primary business in citi corp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Citi technology centre: Pune&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test analytical, logical reasoning, language agnostics, coding
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I hope you found this post helpful. Share it with your friends if you found it useful. And as always, drop a comment if you have any queries and I will respond back to you as soon as possible.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Prepare well for your placements. All the best!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="placement"></category><category term="college"></category><category term="interview"></category></entry><entry><title>The Placement Season</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/07/31/the_placement_season/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-31T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-07-31:blog/2014/07/31/the_placement_season/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The placement season is back. Nothing new, it comes every year but may be...this is new for you and I'm talking to those who're about to witness probably the most important phase of their college life.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
First things first. I'll start with a disclaimer - "Everything written on this space is my personal experience which is definitely not a statistically significant sample size"
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The very first question that comes to a typical final year student- What should I start my preparation with? You've got to do a lot, you know that but you don't know what to start with?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I'll help you out here. I'd started with the &lt;strong&gt;TnPedia&lt;/strong&gt; (this is specific to just students from IIT Kharagpur; others please ignore this).
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Heard of TnPedia? I'm sure you'd have. If not, just download it from dc++. Ohh yes! dc is used for useful stuff as well apart from the 'general daily stuff'. Download the last three years TnPedia and read through the companies you're targeting. This'll give you an overview of what is expected in an interview, what procedures are followed in different companies, you may also gain some insight to what kind of preparation is needed for a particular company.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now that you have given a thorough read to your target companies. Start preparing accordingly. I'll try to give a brief introduction as to what preparation is needed for different profiles.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CONSULTING&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Victor Cheng is your friend. Super-smart guy. Download his video lectures(again dc++)  to get an understanding of what solving a case-study looks like. I'd suggest you to subscribe to his email newsletters as well. Those will help you in slowly gaining the overall idea of consulting.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Preparing for this takes time and you'll have to be persistent. Practise with your wingies, your department friends, anyone...but practise!
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Do the role play.
Some of you become the interviewer and one of you could be the interviewee. I know it sounds weird. But trust me you'll learn a lot. You'll overcome your anxiety of facing the interviewers. At first the role-play thing won't go that fine but with time it'll be smooth and everyone involved will come out beneficial.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Share your feedback about each other. I remember I used to get a lot aggressive while participating in mock group discussions with my friends. You sure will get to know about your weaknesses. Work on these weaknesses before it's too late. By doing this, you get a chance to commit all your mistakes before the real interview and that's a good thing.
Enough words. It's time to execute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Being pro-active is the key."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources for preparation&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the video lectures from dc++. Some 10 videos are there&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subscribe to &lt;a href="http://www.caseinterview.com/homepage-new?utm_expid=6333140-12.n1MK6GEfT5qHocwp2COITg.1&amp;amp;utm_referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fstuffedtomato.quora.com%2FThe-placement-season"&gt;case interview emails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case in point. The pdf is easily available on dc++ or online as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practise your basic math skills. You can't afford to make calculation mistakes in interview. &lt;a href="https://www.caseinterview.com/math/home.php"&gt;CaseInterview&lt;/a&gt; will improve your calculation speed and accuracy
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Case-interview is all about practise. After going through some frameworks you'll feel like you've earned the mastery over this but I guarantee you'll find this wrong once you actually solve a case-study problem in a real interview set-up. So practise, practise and practise.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
That's all for now. I'll add about other job profiles soon as time permits. No more a free bird like I used to be in Kgp. Next update would be on Coding.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CODING&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about coding preparation. Coding was one thing which I'd started learning and practicing only during my placement preparation. Prior to that I never really liked it. Actually I'd never really put much effort into it. And let me tell you this - Coding is interesting stuff to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the resources that I'd found helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/"&gt;GeeksForGeeks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/category/c-arrays/"&gt;Arrays Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/category/c-strings/"&gt;Strings Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/category/linked-list/"&gt;Linked Lists Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/category/tree/"&gt;Trees Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/category/bit-magic/"&gt;Bit Magic Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/category/program-output/"&gt;Output Archives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://quiz.geeksforgeeks.org/"&gt;GeeksQuiz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.in/Cracking-Coding-Interview-Laakmann-McDowell/dp/0984782869/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1468958412&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=cracking+the+coding+interview"&gt;Cracking the Coding interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.in/Data-Structures-Algorithms-Made-Easy/dp/145654988X/ref=sr_1_5?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1468958573&amp;amp;sr=1-5&amp;amp;keywords=Data+Structures+And+Algorithms+Made+Easy"&gt;Data Structures And Algorithms Made Easy&lt;/a&gt;. You get this book in Java, C and C++ version. Get the one in which you're comfortable with. For a starter like me, I'd read the C version.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The above should suffice for a normal coding preparation. I'll add more soon. I'll ask some of my coder friends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all for now. Next update would be on puzzles and brainteasers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best for the placements. Prepare well.
Any help needed? Drop me an email or comment down and I will get back to you as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="interview"></category><category term="placement"></category><category term="preparation"></category><category term="college"></category></entry><entry><title>Beautiful Sadness</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/06/03/beautiful_sadness/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-03T10:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-06-03:blog/2014/06/03/beautiful_sadness/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I woke up this morning, it took me a few moments to realize where I was. I looked around, gained my consciousness and a thought thundered into my mind –I was not in Kgp. Not anymore. Life at Kgp is now a past, a past which will always be cherished and remembered as the guide of all my future endeavors. I had heard that time flies but this fast I didn’t had even an iota of idea. The five years passed by in a blink.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
When  you leave Kgp, you find yourself juggling with thoughts. You experience mixed emotions of both happiness and sadness or rather a term –‘beautiful sadness’ perfectly contain these feelings. You feel sad for the life of peace is over –the phenomenal five years. At the same time you find yourself smiling that Kgp happened to you, that you had your best time here, that you couldn’t have imagined a better college life.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Thank you Kgp for making me what I’m today and know that you’ll play a prominent role in whatever I aspire to become in my future. You are one of the best things that has happened to me in my past five years. Kgp, you have introduced me to some of the most amazing people, well some weird ones as well and a fewer limited editions.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now that we’re separated, I feel the void that has been created between us. But know that no one can ever fill this space of yours. You will always be special and I want you to know that just a thought of yours will automatically bring a smile on my lips. Thank you for the wonderful time we had together. Kgp, thou shall always be missed.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Yours forever,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--Just another Kgpian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photo of kgp" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/beatiful_sadness.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="college"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category></entry><entry><title>My stay at IIT Kharagpur -A synopsis</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/04/16/stay_at_IIT_Kharagpur/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-04-16T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-04-16:blog/2014/04/16/stay_at_IIT_Kharagpur/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mathematics has always been my favorite and when I got Mathematics &amp;amp; Computing, IIT Kharagpur I was on cloud nine. I did a quick Google and landed to the official site of our institute. That was the first time and also the last time when I had paid close attention to each of the tabs in the site. The five years of stay at this land has been phenomenal. I know time flies but this fast, I had no idea.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So I started my first year with full innocence, attended almost all my classes the first few days after which I came to know about this beautiful concept--proxy. The first year passed mostly in making new friends, understanding DC++, giving auditions for societies I had no idea about whatsoever, celebrating birthdays--GPLand attending a few classes. Needless to say, I had screwed my CGPA badly.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Something happened in the very beginning of 2nd year. I got serious with my academics, a little and then I met Professor G.P Raja Sekhar. Well, he needs no introduction. We had 9 credits under him, such a strict professor he was that I managed to attend almost all his classes even the 7:30 ones. That helped and I ended up improving my CGPA. Thank you Sir. I owe this one to you.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Third year went normal –attending a few more classes, this time in our department mostly. I had my internship at IDRBT–an RBI institute in Hyderabad. I feel this internship opportunity is highly under-rated. I urge all you juniors to have a look at this opportunity. I met some juniors and a few seniors of our department. One can find a Kgpian in almost every city. Two months internship got over like a breeze.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Fourth year, this is the time when you get to know the real competition –internship season. Some 10 students could manage to get an internship offer from TnP. The rest of us tried our luck off-campus. I landed up in Mumbai at CRISIL Limited for internship. Mumbai is a city full of life and happenings.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Then came the final year –the placement season. You end up attending more PPTs than your classes. This green site–TnP automatically becomes your homepage. You study more in these four months than all of your first four years combined. A typical day consists of getting CV reviews from your seniors, discussing puzzles, brushing up your coding skills, solving case studies and attending some PPTs. Being proactive is the key. Be well prepared and you will bag your dream job quite easily. Talk to relevant seniors –they know a lot.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I was offered the job of statistical analyst at WalmartLabs. The interview revolved mostly around Statistics, my internships and a few puzzles. Having placed, the last semester is a total delight. You are about to leave your institute so all your emotional chords get stroked.  You wonder doing all things which you might have missed during your four years stay at IIT Kharagpur.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I wish all the very best to my junior batch in their future endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won't get a life like Kgp anywhere else. Make it count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="college"></category></entry><entry><title>Happy Women's Day</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/03/08/happy_women's_day/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-08T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-03-08:blog/2014/03/08/happy_women's_day/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today is 8th March, just another day except that today is women’s day. Women’s day started as a Socialist political movement but over time it has changed to a day when it’s celebrated as a sign of respect and love to women across the world. Women’s day is all about respecting and caring for women around you. Take some time to wish and appreciate women in your life. Not that you shouldn’t love them on any ordinary day. All I’m saying is –&lt;em&gt;It’s their day. Make it special just like you do on someone’s birthday&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Give a call or pay a visit to your mother, wife, daughter, girlfriend, colleague or any women who has stood by you and supported you through the ups and downs of your life. &lt;em&gt;Don’t let this pass like just another day&lt;/em&gt;. Wish them. Tell them that you are thankful to them; I guarantee you their smile –a beautiful smile in return.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I called my mother, wished her, and made her smile. &lt;strong&gt;Did you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="women's day"></category><category term="happy"></category></entry><entry><title>The Walmart Interview</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/03/04/walmart_interview/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-04T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-03-04:blog/2014/03/04/walmart_interview/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Now that you are reading this, I’ll assume that you are someone looking for an opportunity of placement or an internship. Go ahead and read. You have a long journey to cover.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I was offered a job of Statistical Analyst at WalmartLabs. Let me guide you through their placement procedure. Sometime in October, we had the Pre-placement talk (we call it PPT here) where we were introduced to the company’s fundamentals, its businesses and some awesomeness of Walmart. The guy presenting the PPT looked geeky without paying much heed to if we were at all listening. But frankly, he had covered almost everything.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
A month later, we had the online test which was based on statistical questions covering mostly topics such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hypothesis Testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R square&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic probability distribution functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confidence interval
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It also had 2 coding questions out of which I somehow managed to write the logic of one of them. The duration of the test was 90 minutes. I had started with statistical questions first and later moved to the coding part. My friends who had started with the coding questions were not able to attempt some very easy statistics questions. My advice to you is, go for the objective statistics questions first.  I managed to attempt some 17 questions out of a total of 23 questions. Based on the performance in the test a further shortlist of 7 students was declared. Needless to say I was one of them.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So I was selected for the personal interview of WalmartLabs. A lot had to be done. I didn’t know where to start. The first thing I did was to talk to one of my seniors, Manikanta Dinesh. His advice and suggestions helped. A lot. I kept myself surrounded with books for quite a few days. I had interviews for a few other companies as well. I couldn't put all my energy into this one company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Don’t keep all your fruits in one basket. Diversify.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It was day 1, 1st December. I was selected in only one company.  CGPA plays a crucial part. If you have a low CGPA, chances are that you will see students getting shortlisted and your name won’t grace any of the lists. I know that feeling. You see, CGPA plays its part. A strong one.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Next day, Day 2, the only company to appear for – WalmartLabs. So I took all the interview funda from a friend, actually a mentor, Tushar – well, he knew more about interviews at that time, Day 1 placed at Credit Suisse. Having all well-prepared, suited up, drove my cycle to Nalanda Complex. On my way, I kept blabbering and preparing my answers, mostly the introduction part. You see, how you open the interview is important.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Though there were 2 HR guys from Walmart, the 1st round was a Skype interview. I had the experience of talking to my girlfriend at Skype. So 1st round well. That was just said in jest. The 1st round lasted for some 50 minutes. I was asked mostly about my internship at &lt;a href="http://www.idrbt.ac.in/"&gt;IDRBT&lt;/a&gt;. A few puzzles – 3 doors puzzle or the famous &lt;a href="http://www.mathsisfun.com/puzzles/monty-hall.html"&gt;Monty hall&lt;/a&gt;. I was able to answer almost all the puzzles. The interviewer was a CS graduate from IIT Bombay working at WalmartLabs for the past 6 years. How do I know? You ask. Well, I had asked him about it towards the end of the interview where you get to ask questions to the interviewer.
“Never miss this opportunity. Always ask questions. Period.”
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So the 1st round went well. Two of my friends couldn’t make to the 2nd round. This round was a Skype interview as well. This guy, the interviewer was a dude. We talked – I didn’t feel like it was an interview for some 90 minutes. Some very basic concepts of statistics were talked about. Some of which I recall:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you explain probability to your grandmother?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you teach statistics to a layman?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are assumptions of linear regression? What are their implications?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few puzzles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain your work at CRISIL Ltd.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Confident of my grasp at Statistics, the interviewer moved towards courses like Real Analysis and Measure Theory.
Question: Tell me about Cauchy’s law of convergence?
I was blank. Total blank. Few seconds passed. I muttered a few words vaguely. Finally I reiterated confidently. “Sir, I don’t remember this as of now. I didn’t like these courses much. But if you want me to know these subjects, I can very well be versed in them given a day or two.”
Guess what? He was impressed by my say. He said – “Not a problem Manish! I was just curious. You are good in Statistics and that is what mostly matters here.”
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The 3rd round started with only two of us in the game now. The interviewer was a senior executive from US. He asked some general questions from my CV. No more puzzles. This round too lasted for some 50 minutes. Finishing this round, I expected they would announce their result. But they had more in their basket. The other friend of mine couldn’t clear the 3rd round.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The 4th round was an HR round with one of the 2 guys who were present there. This lasted for some 15 minutes. By this time, I was determined – determined to be selected. Cleared it with a smile.
Yes there was a 5th round –a telephonic interview with the senior HR, Bangalore office. Again a 30 minutes interview. Some of the questions I recall:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why Walmart?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is your best buddy? Worst buddy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your greatest weakness?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any questions you would like to ask?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The time now was 7:00 p.m. I was waiting for the result of longest interview of my life, walking restlessly outside the room. Waited for some 15 minutes. I could see the HR guys talking and discussing intensely over phone. A few more minutes passed. The wait was getting heavy now. The HR guy finally came out and with a broad smile, he said –“Congratulations! Welcome to the team.”
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
That moment I knew what success tasted like. I was happy, excited. Overwhelmed! All of a sudden, I felt like a hero. They clicked a photo of me wearing the Walmart cap. They gave me a bag of gifts as a sign of welcome. On my way to hall, I gave a quick call to my father and then to my maa –She said she had been worshipping the whole day. Her prayers had played their charms and she was thankful to her Gods.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Reached my wing, told my friends and then they congratulated –GPL. The night was great. It called for a celebration. We headed to the bar. Time for some drinks.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
One final thought:&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ek din hota hai, ek job hota hai aur ek tum hote ho.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="analytics"></category><category term="statistics"></category><category term="interview"></category><category term="walmart"></category></entry></feed>