<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Manish Barnwal</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://manishbarnwal.github.io/</id><updated>2016-06-29T07:00:00-03:00</updated><entry><title>The Big Data Problem</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/06/29/big_data_problem/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-29T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-06-29:blog/2016/06/29/big_data_problem/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big data&lt;/strong&gt; has become a sensation these days. Anyone and everyone wants to use this in their discussions. When I was still in my college and preparing for campus placements, I had attended almost all the pre-placement talks that companies gave to its prospective candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American Express was one such company that had talked extensively about big data and hadoop in their presentation. I remember clearly, the blank faces that all of us had. We were not able to follow a single term. &lt;strong&gt;Hadoop&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;clusters&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;big data&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;distributed environment&lt;/strong&gt; and many other terms were just bouncers for me. I did try to google them up later but these terms were still alien to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have worked at WalmartLabs for close to 2 years now and the work has mostly been on the big data side. Walmart is one of the largest companies when it comes to capturing the transactions data that we have on daily basis both at the stores and at the e-commerce. Having worked on the big data technologies a little, I felt I would give it a try to make big data and related questions a little easy to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following are few of the questions that I will try to explain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is Big Data? And why should I care about it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the problem with a single laptop?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a cluster?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The data is distributed across the cluster&lt;/em&gt;. What is meant by this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is Hadoop and Spark?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is generating data. Data is the side-product of any work we do. &lt;em&gt;Just like smoke is emitted when things burn, data is created when machines work or interact with each other&lt;/em&gt;. These machines used to emit data in the past as well, but we were not advanced enough to collect the data. The technologies weren’t capable of capturing these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, every other thing is emitting data. Be it the signals from your refrigerator, the air-conditioners in your room, the cars on the street, the videos that you like or dislike on YouTube, your transactions at the nearby Super-market, the posts you make on Facebook. These are all emissions of your day-to-day work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies and analysts want to understand you and your behavior using the data you generate. To give you an idea of how much data is generated, let’s look at the ridiculous amount of data some of the big giants produce on daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook’s daily logs are more than &lt;strong&gt;60 terabytes&lt;/strong&gt; every day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google’s web index is more than &lt;strong&gt;10 petabytes&lt;/strong&gt; of information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Millions of customers visit Walmart stores on daily basis. Imagine the &lt;strong&gt;size of these transactions data&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we need this data? Of course!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every data has a story. With proper analysis and techniques, we can get a lot from data. Now, there will be times when you won’t get anything insightful from it. I consider this also good. Maybe, there is something wrong with the way we are collecting the data and we need to have a look at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far we know that every other thing is puking data. And they are puking in bulk. To get something good out of these pukes, we need to store them somewhere, do our analysis on them and get insights. How do we go about it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storage of this data has never been a problem. The disks are relatively cheap. A terabyte of disk costs ~ $35. So storing them on physical disks is not an issue. What is the problem then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you have an idea how fast the data can be read from a disk? It is still in Mbs/sec. Let us assume a speed of 100 Mbs/sec. With this speed, the time taken to read 1 terabyte of data would be ~ 3 hours! Below is the calculation for 3 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 terabytes = 1000,000 Mb. So the total time ~ 1000,000/100 ~ 10000 seconds ~ 10000/3600 ~ 3 hours&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 hours is too huge a time to read 1 terabyte of data given the amount of data giants like Facebook generates on daily basis. Also, a single machine won’t be able to handle this much data. So what is the solution?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we could distribute the data across multiple machines? Yes, that sounds promising. The data that is big enough to handle by one machine can be distributed across multiple machines such that each machine has some portion of the actual data. Now these machines are interconnected with each other and so there is no issue of interactions between these machines. And that is exactly what a cluster is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;cluster&lt;/em&gt; is a combination of many machines connected to each other. Think of it like this. There is a process by which, my computer and your computer can be connected to each other and we can have a cluster with two nodes or machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, that you have your machines connected with each other in the cluster, you can take advantage of the computation power of each of the machines. And thus, the task which one couldn’t even think of accomplishing by a single machine can now be very easily be done by a cluster of machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is hadoop and Spark? And how are they different?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadoop is a framework that supports the storage and processing of large data sets in a distributed computing environment.It provides massive storage for any kind of data, enormous processing power and the ability to handle virtually limitless concurrent tasks or jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spark is a powerful analytics engine. It is a fast and general engine for large-scale data processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadoop provides both the data storage and processing power whereas Spark is meant for doing analysis and processing of big data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to notice is, Spark is about 10 to 100 times faster than the Hadoop MapReduce framework by making use of in-memory processing compared to persistence storage used by Hadoop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spark is a Swiss army knife of analytics world&lt;/em&gt;. There are various APIs- Python, R, Scala thorough which one can interact with the Spark framework. For machine learning algorithms, there is MlLib which can be used to perform some common analysis like regression, K-means clustering, and classification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will talk more about Spark in future posts. I am exploring it rigorously and plan to write out my understanding of it soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed reading this post and feel a little more familiar with big data now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hit the share button if you would like your friends to read this.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="big data"></category><category term="analytics"></category><category term="hadoop"></category><category term="spark"></category></entry><entry><title>My first attempt at public speaking</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/06/27/first_attempt_at_public%20speaking/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-27T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-06-27:blog/2016/06/27/first_attempt_at_public speaking/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having graduated from college, it was just 6 months into my new job that I was asked to give a tech-talk on &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Data Science&lt;/em&gt;. Imagine the thrill and fright of a fresher when he is presented with a situation like this. The first thing I asked my manager was — how many people are we expecting in the audience? Notice the fright in the question. I was scared that I might screw up in front of a large audience. I may not be able to present the talk eloquently, the audience may laugh at me and all those crappy thoughts that quickly clouds your mind with fear and uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without much thought and ignoring the above questions, I straight away agreed to present the talk. &lt;strong&gt;The plan was simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Commit to the task and then learn how to do it. In a few days, after a lot many iterations I had the presentation ready with me. I had not prepared any script or dialogues for the talk. The reason being, I wanted to give an impromptu talk. Days passed and I got busy in routine office work and meeting project deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing and public-speaking was something that has always fascinated me. I had read many a posts on effective public-speaking. Now was the time to apply whatever I had read about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day had come when I had to give the tech-talk. That morning, I woke up a little early and I looked at a few videos on dealing with the stage-fear. I found this video in particular to be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not that I had not practiced at all. We had a few dry runs. Frankly, I didn’t had the exact lines that I intended to say. I had just planned the overall flow of the talk. As I had read on various blogs on public-speaking, I reached the conference room a little early, walked down the room confidently, talked to some of my colleagues about random topics so as to divert the attention and calm the nerves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within a few minutes, the room got packed with folks from various teams. I hadn’t expected these many people to turn around. Nevertheless, I was happy and confident. I kept saying this to myself — &lt;em&gt;you are going to rock today! So many people have come just to listen to you. You know this stuff. This is your bread and butter&lt;/em&gt;. I took a few deep breaths and started the talk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After first few minutes of the talk, I started reading some of the faces in the audience, trying to understand if they are following what was being spoken. A good proxy for this include people asking questions, nodding to your statements in agreement, and making notes. I could see the audience doing these. So the feedback was good and I continued with the talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not all that easy. I stammered in between, fell short of the right words, the throat felt thirsty, some of the faces in audience looked scary but somehow the confidence in me was at peak. &lt;strong&gt;I was happy talking about something that I enjoyed doing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been almost a year since I had presented this talk. Now when I think about it, I feel good. I feel accomplished. I know I could have screwed up badly. I had to start somewhere. And today I am happy that I did take that chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next time, don’t let that chance pass away. Take that risk, prepare well and make it your first attempt at public speaking. We all need to start somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category></entry><entry><title>Understanding HIVE for data science people</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/06/22/understanding_hive_data_science/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-22T04:43:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-06-22:blog/2016/06/22/understanding_hive_data_science/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been working as Statistical analyst for the last 1.5 years and fortunately I got to work on Hadoop on one of my initial projects. Hadoop sounds scary to a lot of people and I am no exception. In this post, I would make an attempt to explain HIVE-the data warehouse for Hadoop ecosystem. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is HIVE? And why as an analyst I should care about it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HIVE is the part of the Hadoop infrastructure where data gets stored and you can write your query to fetch data from HIVE (tables). Now when I had started working on Hadoop, I knew a little SQL and a tad little of data science. I had take a few courses on Statistics during my college but then who really studies in college! Having allocated to a project which required an understanding of Hadoop, I planned how I need to understand this system so that I can contribute my best to the project.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Hive"></category><category term="hadoop"></category><category term="big data"></category></entry><entry><title>The Placement Season</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/07/31/the_placement_season/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-31T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-07-31:blog/2014/07/31/the_placement_season/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The placement season is back. Nothing new, it comes every year but may be...this is new for you and I'm talking to those who're about to witness probably the most important phase of their college life. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First things first. I'll start with a disclaimer - "Everything written on this space is my personal experience which is definitely not a statistically significant sample size" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very first question that comes to a typical final year student- What should I start my preparation with? You've got to do a lot, you know that but you don't know what to start with?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll help you out here. I'd started with the &lt;strong&gt;TnPedia&lt;/strong&gt; (this is specific to just students from IIT Kharagpur; others please ignore this). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heard of TnPedia? I'm sure you'd have. If not, just download it from dc++. Ohh yes! dc is used for useful stuff as well apart from the 'general daily stuff'. Download the last three years TnPedia and read through the companies you're targeting. This'll give you an overview of what is expected in an interview, what procedures are followed in different companies, you may also gain some insight to what kind of preparation is needed for a particular company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have given a thorough read to your target companies. Start preparing accordingly. I'll try to give a brief introduction as to what preparation is needed for different profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CONSULTING&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Victor Cheng is your friend. Super-smart guy. Download his video lectures(again dc++)  to get an understanding of what solving a case-study looks like. I'd suggest you to subscribe to his email newsletters as well. Those will help you in slowly gaining the overall idea of consulting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preparing for this takes time and you'll have to be persistent. Practise with your wingies, your department friends, anyone...but practise!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do the role play. 
Some of you become the interviewer and one of you could be the interviewee. I know it sounds weird. But trust me you'll learn a lot. You'll overcome your anxiety of facing the interviewers. At first the role-play thing won't go that fine but with time it'll be smooth and everyone involved will come out beneficial. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Share your feedback about each other. I remember I used to get a lot aggressive while participating in mock group discussions with my friends. You sure will get to know about your weaknesses. Work on these weaknesses before it's too late. By doing this, you get a chance to commit all your mistakes before the real interview and that's a good thing. 
Enough words. It's time to execute. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Being pro-active is the key."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Resources for preparation:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the video lectures from dc++. Some 10 videos are there&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subscribe to &lt;a href="http://www.caseinterview.com/homepage-new?utm_expid=6333140-12.n1MK6GEfT5qHocwp2COITg.1&amp;amp;utm_referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fstuffedtomato.quora.com%2FThe-placement-season"&gt;case interview emails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case in point. The pdf is easily available on dc++ or online as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practise your basic math skills. You can't afford to make calculation mistakes in interview. &lt;a href="https://www.caseinterview.com/math/home.php"&gt;CaseInterview&lt;/a&gt; will improve your calculation speed and accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case-interview is all about practise. After going through some frameworks you'll feel like you've earned the mastery over this but I guarantee you'll find this wrong once you actually solve a case-study problem in a real interview set-up. So practise, practise and practise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all for now. I'll add about other job profiles soon as time permits. No more a free bird like I used to be in Kgp. Next update would be on Coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CODING&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about coding preparation. Coding was one thing which I'd started learning and practicing only during my placement preparation. Prior to that I never really liked it. Actually I'd never really put much effort into it. And let me tell you this - Coding is interesting stuff to say the least. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the resources that I'd found helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/"&gt;GeeksForGeeks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arrays Archives - GeeksforGeeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strings Archives - GeeksforGeeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linked Lists Archives - GeeksforGeeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trees Archives - GeeksforGeeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bit Magic Archives - GeeksforGeeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Output Archives - GeeksforGeeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://quiz.geeksforgeeks.org/"&gt;GeeksQuiz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.in/Cracking-Coding-Interview-Laakmann-McDowell/dp/0984782869/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1468958412&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=cracking+the+coding+interview"&gt;Cracking the Coding interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.in/Data-Structures-Algorithms-Made-Easy/dp/145654988X/ref=sr_1_5?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1468958573&amp;amp;sr=1-5&amp;amp;keywords=Data+Structures+And+Algorithms+Made+Easy"&gt;Data Structures And Algorithms Made Easy&lt;/a&gt;. You get this book in C and C++ version as well. Get the one in which you're comfortable with. For a starter like me, I'd read the C version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above should suffice for a normal coding preparation. I'll add more soon. I'll ask some of my coder friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all for now. Next update would be on puzzles and brainteasers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best for the placements. Prepare well.
Any help needed? Drop me an email or comment down and I will get back to you as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="interview"></category><category term="placement"></category><category term="preparation"></category><category term="college"></category></entry><entry><title>Beautiful Sadness</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/06/03/beautiful_sadness/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-03T10:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-06-03:blog/2014/06/03/beautiful_sadness/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I woke up this morning, it took me a few moments to realize where I was. I looked around, gained my consciousness and a thought thundered into my mind –I was not in Kgp. Not anymore. Life at Kgp is now a past, a past which will always be cherished and remembered as the guide of all my future endeavors. I had heard that time flies but this fast I didn’t had even an iota of idea. The five years passed by in a blink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When  you leave Kgp, you find yourself juggling with thoughts. You experience mixed emotions of both happiness and sadness or rather a term –‘beautiful sadness’ perfectly contain these feelings. You feel sad for the life of peace is over –the phenomenal five years. At the same time you find yourself smiling that Kgp happened to you, that you had your best time here, that you couldn’t have imagined a better college life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Kgp for making me what I’m today and know that you’ll play a prominent role in whatever I aspire to become in my future. You are one of the best things that has happened to me in my past five years. Kgp, you have introduced me to some of the most amazing people, well some weird ones as well and a fewer limited editions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re separated, I feel the void that has been created between us. But know that no one can ever fill this space of yours. You will always be special and I want you to know that just a thought of yours will automatically bring a smile on my lips. Thank you for the wonderful time we had together. Kgp, thou shall always be missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yours forever,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--Just another Kgpian &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photo of kgp" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/beatiful_sadness.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="college"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category></entry><entry><title>The Walmart Interview</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/03/04/walmart_interview/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-04T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-03-04:blog/2014/03/04/walmart_interview/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Now that you are reading this, I’ll assume that you are someone looking for an opportunity of placement or an internship. Go ahead and read. You have a long journey to cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was offered a job of Statistical Analyst at WalmartLabs. Let me guide you through their placement procedure. Sometime in October, we had the Pre-placement talk (we call it PPT here) where we were introduced to the company’s fundamentals, its businesses and some awesomeness of Walmart. The guy presenting the PPT looked geeky without paying much heed to if we were at all listening. But frankly, he had covered almost everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A month later, we had the online test which was based on statistical questions covering mostly topics such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hypothesis Testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R square&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic probability distribution functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confidence interval&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also had 2 coding questions out of which I somehow managed to write the logic of one of them. The duration of the test was 90 minutes. I had started with statistical questions first and later moved to the coding part. My friends who had started with the coding questions were not able to attempt some very easy statistics questions. My advice to you is, go for the objective statistics questions first.  I managed to attempt some 17 questions out of a total of 23 questions. Based on the performance in the test a further shortlist of 7 students was declared. Needless to say I was one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I was selected for the personal interview of WalmartLabs. A lot had to be done. I didn’t know where to start. The first thing I did was to talk to one of my seniors, Manikanta Dinesh. His advice and suggestions helped. A lot. I kept myself surrounded with books for quite a few days. I had interviews for a few other companies as well. I couldn't put all my energy into this one company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Don’t keep all your fruits in one basket. Diversify.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was day 1, 1st December. I was selected in only one company.  CGPA plays a crucial part. If you have a low CGPA, chances are that you will see students getting shortlisted and your name won’t grace any of the lists. I know that feeling. You see, CGPA plays its part. A strong one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next day, Day 2, the only company to appear for – WalmartLabs. So I took all the interview funda from a friend, actually a mentor, Tushar – well, he knew more about interviews at that time, Day 1 placed at Credit Suisse. Having all well-prepared, suited up, drove my cycle to Nalanda Complex. On my way, I kept blabbering and preparing my answers, mostly the introduction part. You see, how you open the interview is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though there were 2 HR guys from Walmart, the 1st round was a Skype interview. I had the experience of talking to my girlfriend at Skype. So 1st round well. That was just said in jest. The 1st round lasted for some 50 minutes. I was asked mostly about my internship at &lt;a href="http://www.idrbt.ac.in/"&gt;IDRBT&lt;/a&gt;. A few puzzles – 3 doors puzzle or the famous &lt;a href="http://www.mathsisfun.com/puzzles/monty-hall.html"&gt;Monty hall&lt;/a&gt;. I was able to answer almost all the puzzles. The interviewer was a CS graduate from IIT Bombay working at WalmartLabs for the past 6 years. How do I know? You ask. Well, I had asked him about it towards the end of the interview where you get to ask questions to the interviewer.
“Never miss this opportunity. Always ask questions. Period.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the 1st round went well. Two of my friends couldn’t make to the 2nd round. This round was a Skype interview as well. This guy, the interviewer was a dude. We talked – I didn’t feel like it was an interview for some 90 minutes. Some very basic concepts of statistics were talked about. Some of which I recall:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you explain probability to your grandmother?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you teach statistics to a layman?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are assumptions of linear regression? What are their implications?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few puzzles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain your work at CRISIL Ltd.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confident of my grasp at Statistics, the interviewer moved towards courses like Real Analysis and Measure Theory.
Question: Tell me about Cauchy’s law of convergence?
- I was blank. Total blank. Few seconds passed. I muttered a few words vaguely. Finally I reiterated confidently. “Sir, I don’t remember this as of now. I didn’t like these courses much. But if you want me to know these subjects, I can very well be versed in them given a day or two.”
Guess what? He was impressed by my say. He said – “Not a problem Manish! I was just curious. You are good in Statistics and that is what mostly matters here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3rd round started with only two of us in the game now. The interviewer was a senior executive from US. He asked some general questions from my CV. No more puzzles. This round too lasted for some 50 minutes. Finishing this round, I expected they would announce their result. But they had more in their basket. The other friend of mine couldn’t clear the 3rd round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 4th round was an HR round with one of the 2 guys who were present there. This lasted for some 15 minutes. By this time, I was determined – determined to be selected. Cleared it with a smile.
Yes there was a 5th round –a telephonic interview with the senior HR, Bangalore office. Again a 30 minutes interview. Some of the questions I recall:
- Why Walmart?
- Who is your best buddy? Worst buddy?
- What is your greatest weakness?
- Any questions you would like to ask?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time now was 7:00 p.m. I was waiting for the result of longest interview of my life, walking restlessly outside the room. Waited for some 15 minutes. I could see the HR guys talking and discussing intensely over phone. A few more minutes passed. The wait was getting heavy now. The HR guy finally came out and with a broad smile, he said –“Congratulations! Welcome to the team.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That moment I knew what success tasted like. I was happy, excited. Overwhelmed! All of a sudden, I felt like a hero. They clicked a photo of me wearing the Walmart cap. They gave me a bag of gifts as a sign of welcome. On my way to hall, I gave a quick call to my father and then to my maa –She said she had been worshipping the whole day. Her prayers had played their charms and she was thankful to her Gods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reached my wing, told my friends and then they congratulated –GPL. The night was great. It called for a celebration. We headed to the bar. Time for some drinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final thought: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ek din hota hai, ek job hota hai aur ek tum hote ho.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="analytics"></category><category term="statistics"></category><category term="interview"></category><category term="walmart"></category></entry></feed>