<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Manish Barnwal</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/feeds/life.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://manishbarnwal.github.io/</id><updated>2016-12-22T07:00:00-02:00</updated><entry><title>The filmy Secret Santa</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/12/22/filmy_secret_santa/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-12-22T07:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-12-22:blog/2016/12/22/filmy_secret_santa/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever heard of secret Santa game? If not, you may not appreciate this article. Wait till you join the corporate world. But if you have, secret Santa may ring some bell. This is what will happen when Santa will get introduced to Bollywood.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gift se dar nahi lagta saheb, task se lagta hai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bade bade companies me aise chhote chhote tasks milte rehte hai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rishte me toh hum tumhare Secret Santa lagte hai, naam hum hints ke through bataenge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saara office mujhe Secret Santa ke naam se jaanta hai&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taks pe taks milti rahi hai lekin hint na mila. Mile toh bas tasks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Main aaj bhi feke hue hints nahi uthata&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tasks abhi baaki hai mere dost&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="babu_moshai" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/babu_moshai.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Babu moshai, hints interesting hone chahiye lambe nahi&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It's not the gift that matters...but the task given by your Secret Santa that defines you&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secret Santa is coming&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The practice is on. Hopefully, we will have the song recorded and if it's worth listening to, I will upload it on my &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCbZuY83yIUrbm0dZYP9eFHw/videos?view=0&amp;amp;sort=dd&amp;amp;shelf_id=0"&gt;Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Christmas"></category><category term="office"></category></entry><entry><title>Don’t introduce that bias in your child</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/10/02/bias_in_child/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-10-02T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-10-02:blog/2016/10/02/bias_in_child/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A thought crossed my mind yesterday and just when it was about to get lost in the cloud of many thoughts that scatters in mind…I caught hold of it. I felt I had gathered the maximum out of this thought but I wanted to write about it so that the mind has to think more on it and may be, just may be, I will be able to know more.
Here’s the thought.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every child learns something or the other from every human it spends time with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This statement sounds more promising when we think about it in this context. We tend to become more like our parents because we spend maximum time with them. Our characters and behaviors are imitated from theirs.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
How does it happen that a &lt;em&gt;baniya&lt;/em&gt;’s son is almost always good in calculations and Maths? Why is that? Why doesn’t it tend to behave more like a musician?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Because, the child spends the maximum time with his parents. He sees the kind of work his father does or the daily chores that his mother gets involved it. He might not be paying much attention to all of this throughout his life. But the brain keeps on peeping through. The unconscious learning happens. Or what we call an &lt;strong&gt;unsupervised&lt;/strong&gt; learning in data-science.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In the long run, the best learning happens when it is not enforced. When the child learns on his own, at his own rate.
You want your child to be interested in reading? Make your home a library. Not so fancy or anything. Just surround the room and tables with books. Read it to your baby even when you think the baby doesn’t understand a single word. Let the unsupervised learning happen. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Let the brain enjoy the feel of reading. The idea of living many lives through these books. Every character in these stories will add to the learning. And by the time the child grows, the brain is already hooked to this habit of reading. It has tasted the palatable food of reading. And it can’t survive without it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say, you want him to be a musician. You already know what you need to do.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Do you realize, what have you done by reading out everyday to your child?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
You have introduced a bias in your child’s character. A good bias, I would say. How interesting is that we can relate machine-learning and a child’s learning behaviors. And, we all know what happens to a biased model. It doesn’t work well. There is a &lt;a href="http://scott.fortmann-roe.com/docs/BiasVariance.html"&gt;trade-off&lt;/a&gt; between bias and variance you know.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
While, it’s good to have the child spend time with good people and have a nurtured learning. The child would know about the right things. But don’t stop your child from interacting with someone who is not in your good books. Let us call that someone Asura.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now Asura may not be on good terms with you and you may have legitimate reasons for that. Maybe you feel that Asura is immoral and unscrupulous. But you have seen only a part of Asura’s character. Maybe Asura is an excellent guitar player or a seasoned writer or he could be an expert in other domains. You don’t know.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Let his learning be flexible. Let the bad data be part of his life. Let him enjoy the outliers as well, be it a good or a bad one. With the bad outlier — Asura, make sure you enforce a little of your experience and monitor the child’s learning of good and the evil. Let the supervised learning come into play.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Don’t let your child have limited experiences of just the right things. Don’t limit the datasets in his life or the variance will be huge which again is not a good thing.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Let the learning be both a mix of unsupervised and supervised. A semi-supervised learning we call it in data-science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="learnings"></category><category term="thoughts"></category></entry><entry><title>The most inspiring talk I ever attended live</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/07/26/the_most_inspiring_talk_live/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-07-26T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-07-26:blog/2016/07/26/the_most_inspiring_talk_live/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/walmartlabs-india"&gt;WalmartLabs&lt;/a&gt; India was one of the sponsors of IIT Bombay’s alumni meet and I along with few of my colleagues got a chance to attend the meet-up. I didn’t have much idea about the speakers who were going to present. All I knew was, we wanted to get some good talent for our company and we had set up a booth where we were presenting the work we do at WalmartLabs.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Of all the speakers that presented their talk, one was mesmerizing. I was impressed by this speaker. The way he confidently took the stage. Stood casually by the dais. He didn’t carry any presentation with him unlike the other speakers. There was a charm and calmness in his presence. It was as if he knew that we were eagerly waiting to hear him out.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
He introduced himself as &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ravi-venkatesan-ba15b820"&gt;Ravi Venkatesan&lt;/a&gt;. He gave a brief background about his college, the works he had done, and the great experiences he had in his career of 30 years. Nothing unusual or impressive so far. But when he mentioned the different fields in which he had done his work, I was awestruck. I was not able to digest the fact that he had worked as someone who established Microsoft in India during its early years after having manufactured engines in his previous job. See the difference in the two kinds of work.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Many had asked him not to take this job at Microsoft. That it was not safe to make such a change from working on engines to IT sector. Even his most trusted mentors were not in favor of this change. But this guy wanted to wear this new hat and take this risk. Not to prove anyone wrong but to ensure that later in his life he never had the guilt of not trying.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People generally don’t try new things because they fear the idea of failing. The moment one conquers this feeling and see beyond…all one can see is opportunity, learning, and experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
He was in no hurry to finish up his talk. Slowly, he went on describing his journey of ups-and-downs. His talk was mostly on advices on career.
I remember him mentioning this.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The age of 40 is a magical year. Once you reach this, you start getting serious. You have in front of you, the 40 years you have already lived, you have the list of things you wanted to accomplish, and the things you have actually conquered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next thought that comes to your mind is you don’t have much time left. A few more years and your career will come to a halt. In the next few years, you would like to get the most out of your life. Do not wait to reach this magical year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do things you want to do NOW. Get out of your comfort zone. Take risks. His words were powerful and convincing.
Another anecdote from his life. He had applied for Harvard just after graduating from IIT Bombay. Sadly, he was rejected. Dejected and shattered, he called upon the office asking why was he rejected?
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The person on the other side replied — &lt;em&gt;you don’t have anything different&lt;/em&gt;. Your grades are good and all but how are you different? He had no answer.
Few years passed by. Ravi liked reading about various things. He started writing about these things. His interest towards writing increased exponentially and fortunately at the age of 26, he became the youngest man to have his article published in the &lt;strong&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/strong&gt;. Obviously, he got admitted to Harvard the next time.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
My eyes glistened with awe.
Here was a guy who had not given up. He continued doing things he liked and gave an answer to how he was different from others.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The auditorium echoed with claps from the audience. The speaker opened up for questions from the audience which he patiently answered. There were many in the audience who had more questions to be answered. Time was running short and he had to leave the stage for the next speaker to come.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Did you find the post useful? If you did, share your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="career"></category></entry><entry><title>My first attempt at public speaking</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/06/27/first_attempt_at_public%20speaking/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-27T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-06-27:blog/2016/06/27/first_attempt_at_public speaking/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having graduated from college, it was just 6 months into my new job that I was asked to give a tech-talk on &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Data Science&lt;/em&gt;. Imagine the thrill and fright of a fresher when he is presented with a situation like this. The first thing I asked my manager was — how many people are we expecting in the audience? Notice the fright in the question. I was scared that I might screw up in front of a large audience. I may not be able to present the talk eloquently, the audience may laugh at me and all those crappy thoughts that quickly clouds your mind with fear and uncertainty.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Without much thought and ignoring the above questions, I straight away agreed to present the talk. &lt;strong&gt;The plan was simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Commit to the task and then learn how to do it. In a few days, after a lot many iterations I had the presentation ready with me. I had not prepared any script or dialogues for the talk. The reason being, I wanted to give an impromptu talk. Days passed and I got busy in routine office work and meeting project deadlines.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Writing and public-speaking was something that has always fascinated me. I had read many a posts on effective public-speaking. Now was the time to apply whatever I had read about it.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The day had come when I had to give the tech-talk. That morning, I woke up a little early and I looked at a few videos on dealing with the stage-fear. I found this video in particular to be helpful.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It’s not that I had not practiced at all. We had a few dry runs. Frankly, I didn’t had the exact lines that I intended to say. I had just planned the overall flow of the talk. As I had read on various blogs on public-speaking, I reached the conference room a little early, walked down the room confidently, talked to some of my colleagues about random topics so as to divert the attention and calm the nerves. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Within a few minutes, the room got packed with folks from various teams. I hadn’t expected these many people to turn around. Nevertheless, I was happy and confident. I kept saying this to myself — &lt;em&gt;you are going to rock today! So many people have come just to listen to you. You know this stuff. This is your bread and butter&lt;/em&gt;. I took a few deep breaths and started the talk. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
After first few minutes of the talk, I started reading some of the faces in the audience, trying to understand if they are following what was being spoken. A good proxy for this include people asking questions, nodding to your statements in agreement, and making notes. I could see the audience doing these. So the feedback was good and I continued with the talk.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It was not all that easy. I stammered in between, fell short of the right words, the throat felt thirsty, some of the faces in audience looked scary but somehow the confidence in me was at peak. &lt;strong&gt;I was happy talking about something that I enjoyed doing&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It has been almost a year since I had presented this talk. Now when I think about it, I feel good. I feel accomplished. I know I could have screwed up badly. I had to start somewhere. And today I am happy that I did take that chance.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Next time, don’t let that chance pass away. Take that risk, prepare well and make it your first attempt at public speaking. We all need to start somewhere.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Did you find the article useful? If you did, share your thoughts in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category></entry><entry><title>Beautiful Sadness</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/06/03/beautiful_sadness/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-03T10:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-06-03:blog/2014/06/03/beautiful_sadness/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I woke up this morning, it took me a few moments to realize where I was. I looked around, gained my consciousness and a thought thundered into my mind –I was not in Kgp. Not anymore. Life at Kgp is now a past, a past which will always be cherished and remembered as the guide of all my future endeavors. I had heard that time flies but this fast I didn’t had even an iota of idea. The five years passed by in a blink.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
When  you leave Kgp, you find yourself juggling with thoughts. You experience mixed emotions of both happiness and sadness or rather a term –‘beautiful sadness’ perfectly contain these feelings. You feel sad for the life of peace is over –the phenomenal five years. At the same time you find yourself smiling that Kgp happened to you, that you had your best time here, that you couldn’t have imagined a better college life.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Thank you Kgp for making me what I’m today and know that you’ll play a prominent role in whatever I aspire to become in my future. You are one of the best things that has happened to me in my past five years. Kgp, you have introduced me to some of the most amazing people, well some weird ones as well and a fewer limited editions.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now that we’re separated, I feel the void that has been created between us. But know that no one can ever fill this space of yours. You will always be special and I want you to know that just a thought of yours will automatically bring a smile on my lips. Thank you for the wonderful time we had together. Kgp, thou shall always be missed.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Yours forever,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--Just another Kgpian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photo of kgp" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/beatiful_sadness.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="college"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category></entry><entry><title>My stay at IIT Kharagpur -A synopsis</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/04/16/stay_at_IIT_Kharagpur/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-04-16T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-04-16:blog/2014/04/16/stay_at_IIT_Kharagpur/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mathematics has always been my favorite and when I got Mathematics &amp;amp; Computing, IIT Kharagpur I was on cloud nine. I did a quick Google and landed to the official site of our institute. That was the first time and also the last time when I had paid close attention to each of the tabs in the site. The five years of stay at this land has been phenomenal. I know time flies but this fast, I had no idea.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So I started my first year with full innocence, attended almost all my classes the first few days after which I came to know about this beautiful concept--proxy. The first year passed mostly in making new friends, understanding DC++, giving auditions for societies I had no idea about whatsoever, celebrating birthdays--GPLand attending a few classes. Needless to say, I had screwed my CGPA badly.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Something happened in the very beginning of 2nd year. I got serious with my academics, a little and then I met Professor G.P Raja Sekhar. Well, he needs no introduction. We had 9 credits under him, such a strict professor he was that I managed to attend almost all his classes even the 7:30 ones. That helped and I ended up improving my CGPA. Thank you Sir. I owe this one to you.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Third year went normal –attending a few more classes, this time in our department mostly. I had my internship at IDRBT–an RBI institute in Hyderabad. I feel this internship opportunity is highly under-rated. I urge all you juniors to have a look at this opportunity. I met some juniors and a few seniors of our department. One can find a Kgpian in almost every city. Two months internship got over like a breeze.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Fourth year, this is the time when you get to know the real competition –internship season. Some 10 students could manage to get an internship offer from TnP. The rest of us tried our luck off-campus. I landed up in Mumbai at CRISIL Limited for internship. Mumbai is a city full of life and happenings.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Then came the final year –the placement season. You end up attending more PPTs than your classes. This green site–TnP automatically becomes your homepage. You study more in these four months than all of your first four years combined. A typical day consists of getting CV reviews from your seniors, discussing puzzles, brushing up your coding skills, solving case studies and attending some PPTs. Being proactive is the key. Be well prepared and you will bag your dream job quite easily. Talk to relevant seniors –they know a lot.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I was offered the job of statistical analyst at WalmartLabs. The interview revolved mostly around Statistics, my internships and a few puzzles. Having placed, the last semester is a total delight. You are about to leave your institute so all your emotional chords get stroked.  You wonder doing all things which you might have missed during your four years stay at IIT Kharagpur.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I wish all the very best to my junior batch in their future endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won't get a life like Kgp anywhere else. Make it count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="college"></category></entry><entry><title>Happy Women's Day</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/03/08/happy_women's_day/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-08T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-03-08:blog/2014/03/08/happy_women's_day/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today is 8th March, just another day except that today is women’s day. Women’s day started as a Socialist political movement but over time it has changed to a day when it’s celebrated as a sign of respect and love to women across the world. Women’s day is all about respecting and caring for women around you. Take some time to wish and appreciate women in your life. Not that you shouldn’t love them on any ordinary day. All I’m saying is –&lt;em&gt;It’s their day. Make it special just like you do on someone’s birthday&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Give a call or pay a visit to your mother, wife, daughter, girlfriend, colleague or any women who has stood by you and supported you through the ups and downs of your life. &lt;em&gt;Don’t let this pass like just another day&lt;/em&gt;. Wish them. Tell them that you are thankful to them; I guarantee you their smile –a beautiful smile in return.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I called my mother, wished her, and made her smile. &lt;strong&gt;Did you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="women's day"></category><category term="happy"></category></entry></feed>