<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Manish Barnwal</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/feeds/life-public-speaking.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://manishbarnwal.github.io/</id><updated>2016-06-27T07:00:00-03:00</updated><entry><title>My first attempt at public speaking</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/06/27/first_attempt_at_public%20speaking/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-27T07:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-06-27:blog/2016/06/27/first_attempt_at_public speaking/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having graduated from college, it was just 6 months into my new job that I was asked to give a tech-talk on &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Data Science&lt;/em&gt;. Imagine the thrill and fright of a fresher when he is presented with a situation like this. The first thing I asked my manager was — how many people are we expecting in the audience? Notice the fright in the question. I was scared that I might screw up in front of a large audience. I may not be able to present the talk eloquently, the audience may laugh at me and all those crappy thoughts that quickly clouds your mind with fear and uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without much thought and ignoring the above questions, I straight away agreed to present the talk. &lt;strong&gt;The plan was simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Commit to the task and then learn how to do it. In a few days, after a lot many iterations I had the presentation ready with me. I had not prepared any script or dialogues for the talk. The reason being, I wanted to give an impromptu talk. Days passed and I got busy in routine office work and meeting project deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing and public-speaking was something that has always fascinated me. I had read many a posts on effective public-speaking. Now was the time to apply whatever I had read about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day had come when I had to give the tech-talk. That morning, I woke up a little early and I looked at a few videos on dealing with the stage-fear. I found this video in particular to be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not that I had not practiced at all. We had a few dry runs. Frankly, I didn’t had the exact lines that I intended to say. I had just planned the overall flow of the talk. As I had read on various blogs on public-speaking, I reached the conference room a little early, walked down the room confidently, talked to some of my colleagues about random topics so as to divert the attention and calm the nerves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within a few minutes, the room got packed with folks from various teams. I hadn’t expected these many people to turn around. Nevertheless, I was happy and confident. I kept saying this to myself — &lt;em&gt;you are going to rock today! So many people have come just to listen to you. You know this stuff. This is your bread and butter&lt;/em&gt;. I took a few deep breaths and started the talk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After first few minutes of the talk, I started reading some of the faces in the audience, trying to understand if they are following what was being spoken. A good proxy for this include people asking questions, nodding to your statements in agreement, and making notes. I could see the audience doing these. So the feedback was good and I continued with the talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not all that easy. I stammered in between, fell short of the right words, the throat felt thirsty, some of the faces in audience looked scary but somehow the confidence in me was at peak. &lt;strong&gt;I was happy talking about something that I enjoyed doing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been almost a year since I had presented this talk. Now when I think about it, I feel good. I feel accomplished. I know I could have screwed up badly. I had to start somewhere. And today I am happy that I did take that chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next time, don’t let that chance pass away. Take that risk, prepare well and make it your first attempt at public speaking. We all need to start somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category></entry></feed>