<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Manish Barnwal</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/feeds/life-college.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://manishbarnwal.github.io/</id><updated>2014-06-03T10:00:00-03:00</updated><entry><title>Beautiful Sadness</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2014/06/03/beautiful_sadness/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-03T10:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2014-06-03:blog/2014/06/03/beautiful_sadness/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I woke up this morning, it took me a few moments to realize where I was. I looked around, gained my consciousness and a thought thundered into my mind –I was not in Kgp. Not anymore. Life at Kgp is now a past, a past which will always be cherished and remembered as the guide of all my future endeavors. I had heard that time flies but this fast I didn’t had even an iota of idea. The five years passed by in a blink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When  you leave Kgp, you find yourself juggling with thoughts. You experience mixed emotions of both happiness and sadness or rather a term –‘beautiful sadness’ perfectly contain these feelings. You feel sad for the life of peace is over –the phenomenal five years. At the same time you find yourself smiling that Kgp happened to you, that you had your best time here, that you couldn’t have imagined a better college life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Kgp for making me what I’m today and know that you’ll play a prominent role in whatever I aspire to become in my future. You are one of the best things that has happened to me in my past five years. Kgp, you have introduced me to some of the most amazing people, well some weird ones as well and a fewer limited editions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re separated, I feel the void that has been created between us. But know that no one can ever fill this space of yours. You will always be special and I want you to know that just a thought of yours will automatically bring a smile on my lips. Thank you for the wonderful time we had together. Kgp, thou shall always be missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yours forever,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--Just another Kgpian &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photo of kgp" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/beatiful_sadness.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="college"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category></entry></feed>