<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Manish Barnwal</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/feeds/music.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://manishbarnwal.github.io/</id><updated>2017-11-24T00:00:00-02:00</updated><entry><title>An easy starter to music theory</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2017/11/24/starter_music_theory/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-11-24T00:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2017-11-24:blog/2017/11/24/starter_music_theory/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/music/starter_music_theory/scale-notes.jpg" alt="Photo of twelve notes"
style="width:1200px;height:200px;border:thin solid black;"&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I started playing guitar almost three years back and at that time I had wished it would have been better if I had picked this lovely instrument during my college days. Well, we always repent things we don't do. The guitar was one of such things. But then I read this quote in one of the answers on Quora.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best time to plant a tree was twenty years back and the second best time is NOW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I strongly believe in the power of NOW. So without thinking much, I started learning guitar in the month of June 2014.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
While I have been playing guitar for almost three years, I have also enjoyed learning about the music theory alongside. So I thought it will be a worthy attempt at explaining the music theory I understand. I may not have the answer to all of the questions but I can cover the basics.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In a series of posts, we will talk about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the basic theory of scales&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;how chords are derived from scales&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what it means when we say that the song is in the key of C&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and many more related questions
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
We will become a pro. We will talk music. Let us begin.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
There are seven pure notes in music. They are Sa, Re, Ga, Ma, Pa, Dha, Ni, Sa (same as the first note but higher pitch) in Indian Classical music. The same holds true for Western music as well. Here they are known as Do, Re, Mi, Fa, So, La, Ti, Do. Notes are the key ingredients of music. Notes are what alphabets are in the English language. They are the building blocks.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In this post, I will talk about Western music and to make the concepts relatable I will use the guitar to explain the theory. There are seven pure notes also called as &lt;em&gt;normal notes&lt;/em&gt;. They are C, D, E, F, G, A, B, C. Then there are five &lt;em&gt;accidental notes&lt;/em&gt;. They are named &lt;em&gt;accidental&lt;/em&gt; because they have been derived from the pure notes. The accidental notes are denoted by &lt;strong&gt;#&lt;/strong&gt; (read as sharp) or superscript b (read as flat). For instance, C# is pronounced as C-sharp or D-flat. We will cover this in next few paragraphs.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Not all of the pure notes have an associated accidental note. Only five of the seven normal notes have an associated accidental note. &lt;strong&gt;Notes B and E have no accidental notes i.e B and E have no sharps&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So the accidental notes are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C#, D#, F#, G#, A# or they can also be called as D-flat, E-flat, G-flat, A-flat, and B-flat respectively. So all the notes - C, D, E, F, G, and A have sharps except for B and E notes.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B and E has no sharps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So in total, we have twelve notes in music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/music/starter_music_theory/scale-notes.jpg" alt="Photo of twelve notes"
style="width:1200px;height:200px;border:thin solid black;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would agree with me when I say music is all about ears. But there needs to be some form of measurement that can tell us this note is this far from this note. To elucidate, how do we measure the distance between two cities say A and B? We use Kilometers. Similarly, we have &lt;em&gt;semi-tone&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;tone&lt;/em&gt; to measure the distance between two notes.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So what is a tone? A tone is one full-step from one note to another. As the name suggests, a semi-tone is half of a tone i.e. a semi-tone is half-step from one note to the other. C to D is a full-step and is a tone whereas C to C# is a half-step and is a semi-tone. B to C is also a half-step (remember B has no sharp) so it is a semi-tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/music/starter_music_theory/tone-semi-tone.jpg" alt="Photo of tone and semi-tone"
style="width:1200px;height:200px;border:thin solid black;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, we have covered notes, tone, and semi-tones.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Let us talk about scales. Have you heard of them? A lot of my friends shut down their brain the moment they hear about this word - scales. I try explaining to them that it is not as complicated as people assume. It is simple to understand. Once you have grasped the concept, you need to keep using it in your vocabulary so that you don't forget it. I do the same.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I love explaining to people what scales are or any music theory, hence this post. Another reason for writing this post is I want to use this as a reference for whatever music theory I have understood so far.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Scales - the basic building blocks of chords&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scale is a combination of notes arranged in patterns that provides a template to compose or improvise depending on mood or feel. The notes are arranged in a particular pattern - not any random pattern. We will talk about what these patterns are in next few paragraphs.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So, why are scales important?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scales are important because chords are derived from scales. Scales are building blocks of chords. I will explain how to get chords from a scale in a later post. Coming back to scales, they help you get familiarity with the different notes and help you understand how each note sounds. It is important to understand how each note of guitar sounds. Well, you don't start with hearing each note and remembering how each note sounds. But this should be your long-term goal.  You can't play any combination of notes - they won't sound nice to the ears. Scales are a group of notes which when played together sound like music.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
 Ever seen someone listening to a tune and instantly playing that tune on the guitar? How do they achieve this skill? They have practiced the scales for quite some time. They have spent time transcribing notes on their instrument. Transcribing is the process of finding the note on the guitar that you have in your mind. Well, this takes time and comes with practice. Scales help you achieve this with ease.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are different types of scales?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are broadly two types of scales - major and minor. Well, there are others as well, like pentatonic scales. For starters, we will just focus on major and minor scales.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Remember that there is a pattern in the combination of notes for a scale. Both major and minor scales have a certain pattern in which the notes are arranged and it is this pattern that differentiates their sound and feel. Let us have a look at the major scale.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;Major scale&lt;/strong&gt; - R T T S T T T S&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There you have the major scale. All you need is now to understand what these alphabets mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R stands for root&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T for tone, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S for semi-tone
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 What does a root mean? Root is the main note of the scale. The root and the pattern decide what other notes will be there in the scale. Let us take an example of the simplest scale - C-major scale. So the root here is C note. C-major scale starts with a C, has intermediate notes according to the pattern and then ends with C.
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 Try writing the notes for some other scale, say D-major scale. And check if you have the correct answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on, next is minor scale.
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;Minor scale&lt;/strong&gt; - R T S T T S T T&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us take an example of A-minor scale to see what are the notes of this scale. Below image shows the notes of both C-major scale and A-minor scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/music/starter_music_theory/major-minor-scale.jpg" alt="Photo of major and minor scale"
 style="width:1200px;height:200px;border:thin solid black;"&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The moods of major and minor scale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major and minor scales are often described in terms of the contrasting feel or mood they set. Major scale in general sets a happy and positive mood. Play a C-major scale and you will realise the mood is happy. The minor scale gives a feeling of sadness and melancholy. Play A-minor scale to see if it sets a little sad mood.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
We know there are 12 notes in music (seven pure notes and five accidental). Each of these twelve notes has a corresponding major and a minor scale. So we have 12 major scales and 12 minor scales. Get familiar with scales. This is how my notes on scales look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photo of other scales" src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/music/starter_music_theory/scales-examples.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Try getting the notes of few of the major and minor scales, say G-major scale, D-minor scale or any scale you want. Do the same and I promise this will help you understand scales much better.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now that we know what scales are, we will talk about chords in the next post. And in a few later posts, I will write more on music explaining the basic concepts.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Share this post with people you think are interested in music. Comment if you would like to discuss more on this or have any questions.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="tutorial"></category><category term="manish barnwal"></category></entry><entry><title>Yaadon ki chuskiya</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2017/07/12/yaadon_ki_chuskiya/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-07-12T00:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2017-07-12:blog/2017/07/12/yaadon_ki_chuskiya/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, my friend, Tushar had come to Bangalore to visit me and Rahul before he left for the US for his Masters. He was here for a weekend. We intended to visit places around Bangalore. And we ended up visiting Lal Bagh. I know you are judging me right now. Who goes to Lal Bagh with friends! I had the same thought until I visited this place. Lal Bagh is beautiful and serene. This place is so under-rated. Go there in morning and you will love the place.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Without digressing further, let us talk about how we managed to write a song, play guitar to it, record it on phone and upload it on Youtube. On a Saturday evening, four of us were getting bored. We had just come enjoying our tea from the tea-stall outside my apartment. Tea is important here. See, we were already bored. We didn't have any plans for the night as well. All of us were seated in the room when we thought of writing a song. Ahh, it may sound a little weird but I have done this before. I like writing lyrics of a song at random times.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So, we first decided what should be the theme of the song. Without much discussion, we all agreed on friendship. Since Tushar was leaving for the US, all our thoughts started moving towards that direction. How would he feel after a year when he is seated in a room far from his country. Rahul was the one mostly coming up with the important lines. Dipu and I were mostly into the guitar deciding the music and the lead. Tushar was mostly confused amongst all this. Fidgeting with his mobile. He ended up playing the egg-shaker.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The song is in key of C but the song starts with G chord which gives a different sound to the song. You will see most of the songs in Bollywood, that are in C scale, starts with C-major chord or its relative minor - A-minor. And this sounds repetitive. So I thought of starting with G-major.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
This is what we came up with in four hours. Here is the recording of the song - &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6YfoCfvhpko" target="_blank"&gt;Yaadon Ki Chuskiya&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verse 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chuskiya, chai ki chuskiya... &lt;br&gt;
Chutkiya, yaaron ki chutkiya... &lt;br&gt;
Khushiya, chhoti chhoti khushiya &lt;br&gt;
Humm once... &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yaad aati hai...bas yaad aati hai... &lt;br&gt;
Yaad aati hai...bas yaad aati hai... &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Humming&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmmm...la la la la la... &lt;br&gt;
Hmmm...la la la... &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Verse 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khoya...kyu hoon main khoya &lt;br&gt;
Roya ...kyu hoon main roya &lt;br&gt;
Akela...kyu main akela &lt;br&gt;
Humm once... &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Savera... hai andhera &lt;br&gt;
Pura... phir q adhura &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Savera... hai andhera &lt;br&gt;
Pura... phir kyu adhura &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Humming&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmmm...la la la la la... &lt;br&gt;
Hmmm...la la la... &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Lead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Play the lead&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yaad...aati hai...bas yaad aati hai... &lt;br&gt;
Yaad...aati hai...bas yaad aati hai... &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Humming&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmmm...la la la... &lt;br&gt;
Hmmm...la la la... &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manish&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category><category term="college"></category><category term="original composition"></category><category term="manish barnwal"></category></entry><entry><title>The essence of music in my life</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2017/05/30/music_in_my_life/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-05-30T08:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2017-05-30:blog/2017/05/30/music_in_my_life/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://manishbarnwal.com/images/music/essence_music_life/Youtube-channel-logo.jpg" alt="Photo of music channel" style="width:1250px;height:200px;border:thin solid black;"/&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Guitar is cool. I reckon from my childhood when seeing someone play guitar in movies inspired a sense of great appreciation for the character playing it. Remember &lt;em&gt;Hrithik&lt;/em&gt; from the movie &lt;em&gt;Kaho na pyaar hai&lt;/em&gt;. I always wondered how does one play this instrument.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I loved listening to songs. &lt;em&gt;Sonu Nigam&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;KK&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Kunal Ganjawala&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Neeraj Sridhar&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Wo chali wo chali&lt;/em&gt;, remember this song?) were a few singers who kept me hooked to my CD player. I used to even remember the tough lyrics of a few Punjabi songs - &lt;em&gt;Kunal Ganjawala's Channa ve ghar aa jaa ve&lt;/em&gt;. And then, the next day sing the song with classmates during the recess.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
My mother had this talent of identifying a singer by just listening to the singer's voice. And at that point of time, this was a huge talent for me. I was in awe of this talent of my mother's. I would play a song in the TV room and run to mother in the kitchen and ask her who was the singer. I don't remember even a single time when she flunked my tests.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
So, today when I look back I realize music was something I really enjoyed. Sadly, I was not aware of this then. The idea of music was alien to me. I had never looked at it the way I look at it today.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The closest I could get to music was singing while taking the shower. And that too when father was not around. Singing in front of elders was considered rude. I don't know the reason. Even today, I don't sing in front of my father. Mum is cool. I used to listen and enjoy songs a lot. Many a times while solving the Mathematics problems on simultaneous equations or finding the area of hexagon. Music soothed me. Solving Mathematical problems while listening to music was heaven for the child in me. The best time of the day.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Days passed and the adolescent me got involved in other important responsibilities like attending classes, solving Irodov, DPPs (Daily Practice Problems), preparing for JEE. I was not at home now. I had shifted to Kota far far away from home. Now I was a fan of Atif songs. &lt;em&gt;Dooorie&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pehli nazar mein&lt;/em&gt; were few of the songs to whose tune I used to solve DPPs - finding the maximum range of a projectile or identifying the equation of a plane satisfying a few constraints, or finding the entropy of a system.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Life used to start with breakfast at &lt;em&gt;TTS&lt;/em&gt; (Tina Tea Stall) in &lt;em&gt;Vigyan Nagar&lt;/em&gt;, attend the classes at &lt;em&gt;Gaurav Tower&lt;/em&gt;, have a &lt;em&gt;masala pattiz&lt;/em&gt; (a type of quick snacks) while returning from the class and end with solving the DPPs for that day. This was the routine. Kota has been the learning years of my life. I have learnt so much about life, responsibilities, and people from my stay at Kota. Life had only one aim - Crack the IIT JEE exam.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In the year of 2009 I got admitted to IIT Kharagpur, Maths and Computing. Mathematics was always with me. Place changed, people changed. The world here was different. People were different. The first year passed in getting acquainted to the place. We were masters of our world. Proxy, &lt;em&gt;bhaat&lt;/em&gt; (talk to your friends on the least important topics for hours), mid-sem exams, and most importantly &lt;em&gt;peace&lt;/em&gt; had become part of my life.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In the second year, there was an audition happening for the music club in the hostel. I was naive to think that I sing pretty decent. So, I too went for audition. I failed miserably. There were candidates far better than me. I came back from the audition, talked to my friends, headed to the canteen for tea and the audition chapter was closed.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It was in the winter of year 2013 when my brother, Mukesh had a winter break and he had asked me to recommend what he could do for a month? Without much thought, I suggested him to get a guitar. And he did. My parents tried to intervene saying his studies would get affected. Parents, I tell you, they care a lot about your future. I convinced my mother to get him the guitar or I will buy him one from my stipend. And they agreed.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Mukesh tried his hands on learning guitar for a month. Joined a tutor. But he didn't enjoy it much. Guitar is not everyone's cup of tea. He was more into photography. So later, I got him a DSLR. He has got his repository of clicked photos on Flickr. You can check out his photos at &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/133478356@N02/"&gt;Mukesh Barnwal Flickr&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
My other brother, Mitesh had a knack for music. He used to hum songs a lot. The best one I reckon him singing is the song - &lt;em&gt;Kaho na pyaar hai&lt;/em&gt;. Now, the guitar belonged to Mitesh. He took it to his college in Jalpaiguri. He joined a teacher there. And slowly he picked up the tabs, the chords. He even auditioned for the music club in his college and got selected.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Within no time he started singing song while playing guitar. I still remember how amazed I was when I had first listened to his recorded audio on Whatsapp. I was proud of my brother. I was elated that he had learnt something that a lot of people would love to but failed to invest the time it needs to learn the guitar. You can listen to some of his songs at &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCd0LdTnijWUa31TAfpxjnHg"&gt;Mitesh Barnwal Youtube&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In June 2014, after completing my 20 days trip in Uttarakhand and Chandigarh, I was at home for another 20 days waiting to join Walmart Labs, my first job. I had no idea what to do for these 20 days.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It was one fine morning, Mitesh was practicing on his guitar that I sat next to him and saw him playing the guitar. I asked him, if I could try my hands on the instrument. He agreed. I asked him to teach me something. He smiled. Nevertheless, he explained me a few things- what the strings are named, what each part of the guitar is called and a few other details.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I further enquired about the effective way to learn the guitar. He had a few downloaded tutorials on learning to play guitar. During those few days, I did a few of those tutorials. My guitar sounded pathetic. The sound was not something one would call music. My brother explained, it takes time before you create something soothing. I used to listen to whatever he would say. I have a huge respect for a person who has learnt something from scratch. It shows that the person really enjoys it and has taken the pain to go through the learning curve.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I continued practicing the guitar for those 20 days. Sometimes my mother would enter the room and would ask with a smirk on her face - &lt;em&gt;You too want to learn the guitar, son? Ohh then we would have two guitars!&lt;/em&gt;. My mother hates anything that takes up space in the room. She always had a dislike for guitar as well, because of the space issue. Not so much though, once she got impressed by my brother's performance on guitar.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Post those 20 days, I landed in Bangalore to join the corporate world. Here too, I had a friend who used to play the guitar. I started using his guitar. After a month, I got the first salary credited in my account. The next day me and my friend, Dipu headed to Furtados, a music shop in Koramangala to get the guitar. I got an Epiphone brand guitar.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I started taking classes at &lt;a href="https://www.justinguitar.com/"&gt;justinguitar.com&lt;/a&gt;. This site is the best online resource available for a beginner. After a few months, I realized I needed a tutor for better learning curve. And it has been since then that I have been playing guitar.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The one thing I used to crave for after work in office was to sit down and practice the tabs and chords on the guitar. I have been playing this instrument for the last 2.5 years now.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I am in love with guitar. When I am happy I like to play guitar, when I am tensed I like to play the scales, when I am stressed I like to play something rock. If not never, it is very rare when I don't feel like playing guitar. I hope I continue playing with the same rigor in the coming years and the love for this beauty never abates.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I hope you enjoyed reading this. I will write more on guitar and music in the coming few days.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="thoughts"></category><category term="nostalgia"></category><category term="manish barnwal"></category></entry><entry><title>Coldplay-Fix you | Ghar aa jaao</title><link href="http://manishbarnwal.github.io/blog/2016/11/24/ghar_aa_jaao/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-11-24T07:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>Manish Barnwal</name></author><id>tag:manishbarnwal.github.io,2016-11-24:blog/2016/11/24/ghar_aa_jaao/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month on a mundane weekend, I was practicing this song - Fix you by Coldplay when my friend, Dipu came to the room. He stood there for some time to understand what I was trying to play. I am not that pro on guitar yet. Chances are you may want to throw me and my guitar out of your sight.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
After some trouble, Dipu finally guessed the song and randomly uttered some lines in Hindi along the tune of the original song. And when he was bored, he left the room. I continued my attempt to make the song perfect on the guitar. It was then when I thought what if I write the complete song in Hindi along the tune of the original.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Without much thought, I picked up my notebook and started scribbling few lines. Later, Dipu also joined me in this attempt and below is the final song that we came up with.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Verse 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab har koshish pe ho jaati hai haar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab milta nahi jo ho tera pyaar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab saath nahin ho mera wo yaar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Akela hoon main...&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Verse 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab lagta hai sab gaya hai bikhar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab lagta hai suna, bin tere sheher&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jab aati nahi ho tum nazar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sab kuch hai soo... oo... na&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghar aa jaao tum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sath seh lenge hum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kal fir aayega&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Verse 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sadkon pe hoon, ab main khada&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aakhon me hain, bas chehra tera&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur hoton pe hai, bas vaada tera&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tujh sang hamesha...aaa&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghar aa jaao tum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sath seh lenge hum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kal fir aayega&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Bridge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aasoon bahein, tere chehre pe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur main kuch na kar paaya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aasoon bahein, tere chehre pe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur main...&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Aasoo bahein tere chehre pe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur main bebas hoon yahan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aasoo bahein tere chehre pe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aur main...&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghar aa jaao tum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sath seh lenge hum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kal fir aayega&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Chorus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghar aa jaao tum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sath seh lenge hum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kal fir aayega&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Here is how the song sounds. Give it a listen &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8NDH2L5R27w" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="original composition"></category><category term="manish barnwal"></category></entry></feed>